<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>Yet Another Lambda Blog</title>
        <link>https://jstolarek.github.io</link>
        <description><![CDATA[A language that doesn't affect the way you think about programming, is not worth knowing]]></description>
        <atom:link href="https://jstolarek.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2023 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Salerno '43</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 25/10/2023
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="salerno-43">Salerno ’43</h1>
<p>In 2023 I finally managed to return to wargaming. This has been an important
hobby of mine for well over a decade now, but I had few playing partners when I
moved abroad. In the past 12 months I not only renewed several of my wargaming
friendships, but also bought a new wargame for the first time in several years.
My choice was <a href="https://www.gmtgames.com/p-868-salerno-43.aspx">Salerno ’43 published by GMT
Games</a> and designed by Mark
Simonitch, a designer whose several games I have played in the past and was
never disappointed with them.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/salerno_43_box.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/salerno_43_box_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
GMT Games has greatly improved in the cover art department in the recent years.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Mark Simonitch is a designer specializing in World War II hex-and-counter games.
His games typically focus on a single military operation lasting several weeks.
His previous games include Ardennes ’44 (Battle of the Bulge in late 1944),
Normandy ’44 (the Allied invasion of France, obviously), France ’40 (German
invasion of Belgium and France as well as Dunkirk evacuation), Holland ’44
(Operation Market Garden), and several others.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/ardennes_44.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/ardennes_44_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Ardennes ’44. An unfolding German advance through the Ardennes forest.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/france_40.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/france_40_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
France ’40. Dunkirk evacuation underway.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/ukraine_43.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/ukraine_43_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Ukraine ’43. A military front across Ukraine looks eerily in 2023.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The games often come with several scenarios, one of which is typically a shorter
game that can be played in a couple of hours. Usually there’s also a longer
campaign scenario, which might require more than one playing session to
complete. Of course this isn’t a strict rule. For example both scenarios that
come with France ’40 can be played in under 5 hours, which by wargaming
standards makes for a short game. I personally lean towards these playing
experiences that don’t exceed 5 hours. And so my attention was caught by
Salerno ’43. It is a fairly recent design by Mark Simonitch and it plays on a
very small map - again, by wargaming standards. This suggested a shorter and
simpler game that has a chance of getting to the table more often than it’s
larger siblings.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/salerno_43_at_start.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/salerno_43_at_start_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Initial setup with the Allies prepared for invasion.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Salerno ’43 tells the story of Operation Avalanche, the Allied amphibious
landing near the Italian city of Salerno in September 1943. One player assumes
the role of the defending Germans, the other of the invading American and the
British Commonwealth troops. So far I have only played the short scenario,
which lasts eight turns and, once proficient with the rules, takes around 3
hours to play. There is also a 22-turn campaign scenario, which I am yet to try
out. In all Mark Simonitch’s games the turns are constructed such that one
player moves all his units, then conducts all combats, and then the other player
gets their turn to do the same. Each player’s turn also contains various
“bookkeeping phases”, when players receive reinforcements and check whether
their units are in supply. The actual details are more complicated than that,
but that’s the gist.</p>
<p>Speaking of simplicity, the game isn’t exactly as simple as I had hoped for. I
mean, sure, the map is small. Just look:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/salerno_43_map.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/salerno_43_map_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Playing area is really small.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Not only the map is 22” by 25.5”, instead of the usual 22” by 34”, but also over
a third of the game board is covered by the sea. This makes the playing area
small. The unit density is also fairly low, which is actually one of the
trademarks of Mark Simonitch’s designs. The rules, however, are comparable in
complexity to other, larger titles. One reason for this is the need to cover
the naval invasion and provide mechanics for troops landing on the beaches.
Another chunk of complexity is due to terrain in that area of Italy, which is
mostly hills and mountains, with only a small pocket of plains south of Salerno.
Then there’s a bunch of smaller rules to cover things like aerial and naval
support, naval transport, weather, special units, or rare combat corner cases
such as city battles. All that adds up to a game of rule complexity similar to
previous designs, just with a smaller amount of counters and thus playing a bit
faster. But not much faster if you haven’t internalized the rules and keep
checking them in the rulebook.</p>
<p>An important question when discussing wargames is that of balance, i.e. do both
sides have an equal chance of winning? Of course, when designing wargames that
recreate historical battles this becomes tricky, since many campaigns have been
single-sided. A good example of this is the already mentioned Operation Dynamo
(Dunkirk evacuation) depicted in France ‘40. Historically, this has been a
decisive German victory, though in the end the British managed to successfully
retreat a significant number of the BEF soldiers. And so the game must recreate
that historical imbalance of forces and outcomes, at the same allowing both
players to achieve victory. Otherwise it wouldn’t be a fun game if one player
was doomed to lose from the start. And so play balance is achieved by measuring
players’ effectiveness against their historical counterparts, typically by
assigning victory points (VPs) to certain strategic locations on the map, and
then designing scenarios such that in order to win the players need to reach
these locations in a given time frame.</p>
<p>Salerno ’43 uses this exact solution, but I am not entirely happy with the
resulting gaming experience, at least in the short scenario. In order to win
the Allied player must accumulate at least 8 VPs points by reaching designated
objectives. Here’s how the objectives are laid out on the map - values in red
circles are Victory Points:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/salerno_43_vps.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/salerno_43_vps.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Objectives near the landing areas.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I am yet to see a game where the Allies capture Eboli, Nocera Inferiore or
anything north of it. I imagine this could be possible with a combination of
lucky die rolls or German player incompetence, but in the games I played so far
the Allies weren’t even able to approach any of these cities, let alone attempt
to capture them. The remaining objectives total at exactly 8 VPs, leaving the
Allies no room for any strategic decision making. I also note that VPs can be
gained or lost by eliminating certain critical units such as artillery or
beachheads. Artillery losses don’t really happen, but unlucky die rolls can
result in losing a beachhead. In fact same goes for Salerno - it has to be
captured by the Rangers and Commandos on turn one. If that fails, capturing it
later becomes nearly impossible. In other words, with unlucky die rolls on the
first turn leading to not capturing Salerno the fate of the Allied player is
practically sealed.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/salerno_43_salerno.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/salerno_43_salerno_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
The Allies can’t win without capturing Salerno.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/salerno_43_end.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/salerno_43_end_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
During this game the Germans not only managed to deny Salerno to the Allies, but also drove them back from Vietri sul Mare.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<a href="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/salerno_43_battipaglia.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43/salerno_43_battipaglia_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figure>
<figcaption>
Battipaglia is another city that the Allies must capture in order to win.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>That being said, while there isn’t much room for larger strategic decisions in
the short scenario, there are tons of smaller tactical decisions to be made.
And while the broad picture of the invasion was similar in all the games I
played so far, at a tactical level all the games were completely different.
There’s lots of manoeuvring to get units into favourable positions, which is
crucial given the amount of hills and rivers. On that front the game absolutely
delivers, requiring the player to think a lot about how to best utilize
available assets, and demanding some really difficult decisions.</p>
<p>All in all, I did enjoy my games of Salerno ’43. The game isn’t as simple in
terms of rules as I hoped it will be, but small playing area and low unit count
makes for a quick wargaming experience. I also note that history buffs will
spot some minor simplifications that could be seen as historical inaccuracies.
I personally find these absolutely irrelevant.</p>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>25/10/2023</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-10-25-salerno-43.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>LineageOS on Samsung S7&#58; An Experience Report</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-10-09-lineageos-on-samsung-s7-an-experience-report.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 09/10/2023
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="lineageos-on-samsung-s7-an-experience-report">LineageOS on Samsung S7: An Experience Report</h1>
<p>I don’t have much love for smartphones. While I admit they can be useful at
times, I absolutely detest their ecosystems ‒ both Android and Apple
‒ that primarily exist not to fulfil the needs of the users but those of
the big tech companies. This is a regrettable state of things and any efforts
to change this have not seen widespread success. That being said, a year ago I
decided to run an experiment. Android is after all a free, open-source
software. I thought there should be a way of installing a vanilla version of
Android that lacks Google spyware that manufacturers bundle with the phones.
After exploring the topic I decided to install
<a href="https://lineageos.org/">LineageOS</a>, an Android-based free and open source
operating system for smartphones, on my Samsung S7.</p>
<p>Several weeks ago the said Samsung phone died due to internal memory failure. I
think this is a good moment to share an experience report from a year of using
LineageOS.</p>
<h2 id="android-ecosystem">Android ecosystem</h2>
<p>Vanilla Android is an open source software. If so, then how come it is such a
threat to user’s privacy? Well, that’s because of <a href="https://developers.google.com/android/guides/overview">Google Play
Services</a><a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a>, a set of
libraries that phone manufacturers install on retail distributions of Android.
Crucially, many applications require Google Play Services in order to run
correctly. Hence comes the first choice one needs to make when deciding to use
LineageOS. It is possible to use LineageOS without Google Play Services, but
some applications will refuse to work or will experience issues. See
<a href="https://plexus.techlore.tech/">Plexus</a> project for a community-maintained list
of applications. Alternatively, it is possible to install Google Play Services
on LineageOS and have all applications run without problems, but to me this
defeats the purpose of using LineageOS.</p>
<p>There is, however, a third option ‒ an open-source implementation of
Google Play Services known as <a href="https://microg.org/">microG</a>. I did some
superficial reading on microG and concluded that I don’t fully understand how it
works. In particular, I couldn’t figure out how the presence of microG affects
my privacy. As a result I decided to use LineageOS without microG, which is
exactly how LineageOS is distributed by default.</p>
<h2 id="obtaining-lineageos">Obtaining LineageOS</h2>
<p>Let’s talk about getting LineageOS onto your phone. Developers maintain <a href="https://wiki.lineageos.org/devices/">a list
of supported devices</a>, for which official
builds are available. The list isn’t short, but don’t be surprised if your
phone is not there. Mine used to be supported at some point in the past, but
that support was dropped due to lack of active maintainer. This presented me
with the first serious problem: how do I obtain an image of LineageOS if it
is not available on the official website?</p>
<p>Technically, there are two solutions. One is to use unofficial ROMs
(i.e. pre-built images) available at the <a href="https://forum.xda-developers.com/">XDA
Forums</a>. These images often come with extra
software, most commonly the already mentioned microG or GSF. They are also
often built on a version of Android that is higher than the one officially
available for the phone. However, there is a big issue of trust here. It
generally seems that the uploaded builds are considered trusted, in a sense that
people just trust that the uploaded images are safe. Except there is no way of
really verifying that the images do not contain any malware or spyware or
whatnot. My instinct was not to use those builds.</p>
<p>I was left with the second solution: building the ROM image myself. Since my
phone used to be officially supported there were build instructions available
for it, except they turned out to be highly inaccurate. Long story short, it
took me 3 weeks to solve the problems I was running into while building, which
is more than most users are willing to spend on installing a new system to their
phone. Even worse, after installing my newly-built image it turned out that the
Bluetooth doesn’t work. A case of missing firmware perhaps?</p>
<p>In the end I managed to find an archive of old official LineageOS images located
on a Russian FTP server that also hosted various leaked corporate data and a
North Korean Linux distribution known as RedStar OS. Admittedly, this source
was more dubious than the XDA Forums, but the archive of images looked
legitimate and so I put my security concerns aside. This image turned out to
work without any issues, including the previously broken Bluetooth.</p>
<h2 id="flashing-os-image-onto-the-phone">Flashing OS image onto the phone</h2>
<p>Once I obtained the installation image I had to flash it onto my phone. In the
past this typically required some sort of jailbreak. Nowadays it seems that
more and more manufacturers permit installation of custom images without a need
for jailbreaking the phone<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a>. This was indeed the case for my Samsung S7.</p>
<p>Image installation is a two stage process. Firstly, I had to install a custom
recovery image onto the phone. My understanding of a recovery image is that
this is a low-level bootloader that allows installing a custom OS image as well
as performing low-level management of the phone. In my case the recovery image
contained <a href="https://twrp.me/faq/whatistwrp.html">TWRP</a>. Once the recovery image
was installed I could then flash the LineageOS image. All of that was done by
connecting the phone to a PC via a USB cable and required having two tools on my
Linux - <code>adb</code> and <code>fastboot</code>.</p>
<p>I have to say that booting LineageOS for the first time was stressful. I was
afraid that I might brick my phone, but none of that happened. All worked as
expected and the new system booted without problems.</p>
<h2 id="getting-applications">Getting applications</h2>
<p>Once the system was up and running I proceeded with installing applications on
it. One method of doing it is installing applications distributed in .apk files
via USB. This is not a convenient way of getting new software onto the phone,
but it is required to at least install <a href="https://f-droid.org/">F-Droid</a>. F-Droid
is an application store, except that it contains open source applications<a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"><sup>3</sup></a>.
Using F-Droid I installed <a href="https://github.com/whyorean/AuroraStore">Aurora
Store</a>, an open-source Google Play
Store client that allows you to install applications from the official store.
At this point one can just install needed applications in the usual way.</p>
<h2 id="the-user-experience">The user experience</h2>
<p>Let’s talk about the most important thing - how was the user experience? In
short, it was good but somewhat worse than the original OS provided by Samsung.
Here is a list of problems I ran into.</p>
<p>Firstly, the official Samsung OS was based on Android 8, whereas LineageOS 14 I
installed onto the phone was based on Android 7. That in itself made for a
noticeable downgrade. It took me quite a while to get used to the look and feel
of applications shipped with LineageOS. In particular, I didn’t like how some
of the applications, e.g. SMS app, did not even allow me to change the colour.
Note also that we are talking about very old Android and LineageOS versions. I
suspect that both the looks of applications as well as customization options are
very different in the more recent versions.</p>
<p>Another downgrade that was obvious from the very beginning was the keyboard. It
not only, similarly to other system apps, lacked customization options but it
also provided noticeably worse hints. I had to find a replacement. This was a
difficult choice to make. Sure, hints in Google’s GBoard are great, but using
it comes at the expense of privacy. Indeed, keyboard software is at the core of
a system’s privacy and security since anything you type (emails, passwords)
comes through that application. After extended research I decided to go with
<a href="https://anysoftkeyboard.github.io/">AnySoftKeyboard</a>. I don’t know if this was
the best choice, but it definitely was an acceptable choice. But again I have
to stress: the quality of hints was noticeably worse than with GBoard. At least
for the Polish language, which I primarily use.</p>
<p>I mentioned the Aurora Store as a client to Google Play Store. One nice thing
it can do is allow application downloads via an anonymous account. Obviously,
anonymous login will not allow you to access paid apps assigned to your Google
account, if you happen to have such. What was an issue is that the app would
break every now and then. This is inherent in these kinds of open-source
replacements for proprietary clients: every time the API changes the client app
breaks. On certain occasions I also found that anonymous downloads did not
work, but logging into my Google account would solve the problem<a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4" role="doc-noteref"><sup>4</sup></a>. One very
nice feature that Aurora Store has, but Google’s official software lacks, is the
ability to filter apps based on in-app advertisements and reliance on GSF. This
is a great feature and I miss it now that I’m back on a Google-based Android.</p>
<p>As mentioned earlier, applications that require GSF can experience problems.
This will range from certain functionalities being broken, e.g. Discord not
showing notifications, to not running at all. I personally was not seriously
affected by this, but I am not a heavy smartphone user. In particular I do not
use social media and their associated applications, and from what I read these
can exhibit problems. The only application that I had to give up was InPost
Mobile, which is an app by a delivery company that operates a dense network of
parcel lockers throughout Poland. This wasn’t a big problem though since I can
still use these parcel lockers via SMS messages.</p>
<p>I also experienced two serious usability issues. The first one was with the
loudspeaker. Apparently, LineageOS couldn’t do echo cancellation so whenever I
switched to a loudspeaker during a call, the caller would hear their own voice.
This rendered the loudspeaker practically unusable. The second issue was photo
quality, which had decreased dramatically with photos coming out blurry and with
a lot of grain. I experimented with several photo taking applications,
including ones that have really good reviews on the web, but none of them
improved the situation, and many made even worse photos. <strong>As a result my phone
became almost useless as a camera and I ended up borrowing my wife’s phone
whenever I had to take photos. This is probably the single biggest downside I
experienced from switching to LineageOS.</strong></p>
<p>Another minor issue I experienced was when attempting to contact Discord support
with a bug report. As soon as they heard I am on an Android without GSF they
dismissed me by saying they <em>“only support Android devices that have the Google
Play Store pre-installed”</em>. I recognize this is not a technical issue with
LineageOS itself, but it might be worth being aware of this kind of attitude
from the developers.</p>
<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>The above list of encountered issues might look discouraging, but for me the
pros of using LineageOS outweigh the cons. Most importantly, having a system
with no Google services that constantly spy on me was a big win. Of course,
proprietary apps still have their own telemetry and it doesn’t look like there’s
anything that can be done about it in the Android ecosystem, other than a
radical move of not using such apps. I also realize that for some people
stepping away from using Google services might be a radical move in itself.</p>
<p>At no time of using LineageOS had I thought of switching to something else.
This is in stark contrast with my current smartphone. After my S7 died I had to
get a new phone ASAP, and being temporarily low on budget I went with the Xiaomi
Redmi Note 10 Pro. Oh my, was that a mistake. The phone comes with
advertisements built into system applications, including aggressive
advertisements that take over the whole screen. Theoretically these ads can be
disabled, but sometimes that doesn’t work and ads display anyway. There’s also
lots of annoying bugs and, despite good technical specs of the phone, the
overall experience isn’t great. Luckily, LineageOS is officially supported on
the phone so I see myself installing LineageOS again at some point in the
relatively near future.</p>
<section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Google Play Services are also sometimes referred to as Google Software
Framework ‒ shortened as GSF ‒ and I will use both terms
interchangeably.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Keep in mind that this usually voids the warranty.<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>In the retro-modding community you’d just call them homebrew. Not sure
whether the term applies here.<a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>This means logging into my account only in Aurora Store, not on the phone
itself. Since LineageOS comes without GSF there is even no way to log
into Google account on the phone.<a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>09/10/2023</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-10-09-lineageos-on-samsung-s7-an-experience-report.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>System Shock remake</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-10-01-system-shock-remake.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[After years of troubled development System Shock remake is finally here and it is one of the best immersive sims I have seen in years.]]></description>
    <pubDate>01/10/2023</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-10-01-system-shock-remake.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>All the things I've ever done wrong with my websites</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-07-12-all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 12/07/2023
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites">All the things I’ve ever done wrong with my websites</h1>
<p>This post has been long in the making. I started writing it in March, and now,
four months later, it is finally finished. I was inspired by Fabien Sanglard’s
<a href="https://fabiensanglard.net/html/index.html">post about technical aspects of his
blog</a> and it made me reflect on all
my past and present web sites and things I did wrong when creating and hosting
them. I’ve been maintaining some form of online presence, whether a homepage, a
blog, or a fansite, for the past 23 years so there was a lot to reflect on.
Here’s a chronological list.</p>
<h2 id="fremen-zone">Fremen Zone</h2>
<p>This will be a trip down memory lane. Fremen Zone was my fansite dedicated to
Frank Herbert’s “Dune” novel and related works such as games and movies. I
started it when I was in high school back in 1999. By that time I already knew
how to program, but creating web sites was a new thing for me. I wanted both to
share my fascination with the Dune universe as well as learn how to create web
pages. This was also the time when lots of online portals offered free hosting.
In the west this was typically GeoCities, but here in Poland I used Onet. When
signing up one would not only get an email address but also a few megabytes of
disk space to host a website. I know that by today’s standards 2 or 5
megabytes is laughably low, but back then it was more than enough. Later in its
lifetime Fremen Zone changed hosting and included some multimedia downloads,
growing the page size to a total of around 75 megabytes.</p>
<p>Fremen Zone was initially intended to be dedicated to the Dune II strategy game.
A very rough first prototype looked like this (this is the highest resolution
screenshot I have):</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<img src="/images/posts/2023-07-12-all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites/fz_proto_1.png" />
<figcaption>
First prototype.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It was quickly discarded and replaced with another prototype, this time with
scope extended to contain the books. As you can see the working name of the
website was also different:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<img src="/images/posts/2023-07-12-all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites/fz_proto_2.png" />
<figcaption>
Second prototype.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Both prototypes were created using Microsoft FrontPage, a WYSIWYG HTML editor.
However, I quickly realized that, firstly, I am not learning much by using this
kind of tool and, secondly, that the generated HTML is bloated and unlikely to
work on web browsers other than Internet Explorer, such as Netscape Navigator.
As a result I switched to writing HTML and CSS by hand. The results were very
good and I think they still hold up well even today:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<img src="/images/posts/2023-07-12-all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites/fz_old.jpg" />
<figcaption>
Fremen Zone displayed in Internet Explorer sometime in the early noughties.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Fremen Zone went online in June 2000. The process of first creating and then
maintaining it was a lot different from what we do today. First and foremost, I
didn’t have Internet access at home. This meant I had to update all the files
in advance and then upload them when visiting my dad’s work during the weekend.
These weekend visits were also the only time when I could browse the Internet to
find any information for the website, although this wasn’t a big problem since
practically all of the content was created by me based on reading the books,
playing the games, and watching the movies. The only significant exception were
reviews of the last three books in the original Dune cycle, which I have not yet
read when I started creating Fremen Zone. Luckily, Dune was quite a popular
books amongst my peers and a friend of mine who read all the books agreed to
provide missing reviews. With no Internet access at home this was a
logistically complicated process, since said friend lived in a different part of
city. We spent a long time on the phone discussing the books, the page, and
writing reviews, which resulted in phone bills going up significantly. Again,
not a trivial problem in late 90s Poland. I also mentioned that Fremen Zone
contained some downloads. These included, among others, Dune and Dune II games,
which back then were considered abandonware<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a>.</p>
<p>Fremen Zone was last updated in 2004. At some point there wasn’t much more to
write about and the page simply existed without any supervision. It eventually
withered away and disappeared when its free hosting was closed down. I have no
recollection of when that happened. A copy of the website has been sitting on
my hard drive all this time and as I was writing this post I thought to myself
“why not bring Fremen Zone” back to life? <a href="https://jstolarek.github.io/fremenzone/">And so I
did</a>. Using GitHub as a hosting
service it took two afternoons to put it online. In fact it could have been
hosted as it was, but I wanted to move away from ISO-8859-2 and CP-1250
encodings in favour of UTF-8. I also wanted to replace self-extracting RAR
archives with ZIP ones.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-07-12-all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites/fz_today.png"><img src="/images/posts/2023-07-12-all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites/fz_today_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Revived Fremen Zone hosted on GitHub Pages.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In retrospect I am very happy about how the Fremen Zone turned out. The fact
that after over two decades the page “just works” shows how future-proof pure
that HTML and CSS are. Perhaps the only complaint that could be made is that it
doesn’t look good on mobile devices, but honestly speaking I couldn’t care less
about that. When it comes to the Fremen Zone I can proudly say I made no
mistakes. As you will see below this is not the case for my other websites.</p>
<p>Lessons learned:</p>
<ul>
<li>Filling the website with content is lots of fun.</li>
<li>Hand-written HTML and CSS are great, though full-scale redesigns are
tedious.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="evolutionary-biology-blog-at-blogger.com">Evolutionary biology blog at blogger.com</h2>
<p>Towards the end of my university studies I picked interest in evolutionary
biology. I read lots of books on the subject and I have to credit works of
Charles Darwin, Richard Dawkins, and E. O. Wilson as being the biggest influence
in forming my approach to research and science in general. (For the record, I
studied computer science, not biology.) I decided to turn that fascination of
biology into a blog. It contained mostly reviews of popular science books about
biology, myrmecology, cognitive science, and occasionally modern physics and
cosmology.</p>
<p>I decided to host my blog using one of many blogging services available in the
noughties. After some consideration I went with Google’s Blogger, with first
post being published in 2008. Blogger is designed as a user-friendly CMS with
some (limited) options to customise layout. Post editing is done using an
online WYSIWYG editor, with everything being saved immediately (at least in
theory). Over time I grew to dislike that editor. It isn’t a horribly bad
experience but editing inside a text field embedded in a browser window is far
from being the best possible experience. There was always the option to switch
it to pure HTML mode, but as you might guess two modes weren’t perfectly
compatible as code generated from the editor wasn’t exactly what one would write
by hand, and conversely, code written by hand sometimes wasn’t parsed correctly
in WYSIWYG mode.</p>
<p>In the end I think the biggest problem with Blogger was taking ownership of
created content. There is the ever-looming threat of service joining the
<a href="https://killedbygoogle.com/">Google Graveyard</a>. Although Blogger allows to
export all posts to an XML file, it seems to be only able to export text, with
all images being lost in the export process.</p>
<p>Lessons learned:</p>
<ul>
<li>Do not use a service that doesn’t allow you to export all created content.
Always make sure to own everything that you created. Ideally, don’t depend
on an external service at all.</li>
<li>Online WYSIWYG editors are somewhat inconvenient.</li>
<li>Blogging is fun.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="professional-homepage-version-1-plain-html">Professional homepage, version 1: plain HTML</h2>
<p>In late 2008 I started my work at Politechnika Łódzka<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a> (PŁ for short). Back
then PŁ didn’t have a unified online learning platform and so each employee used
their personal web page to provide learning materials for the students. I had
to create such a page for myself and since I needed it ASAP I chose the easiest
solution: hand-written HTML with practically no CSS, other than white
background. The page wasn’t fancy but it did the job of delivering basic
information.</p>
<p>Lessons learned:</p>
<ul>
<li>Again, hand-written HTML and CSS are great.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="professional-homepage-version-2-dokuwiki">Professional homepage, version 2: DokuWiki</h2>
<p>That first version of my professional homepage was intended to be a temporary
solution but in the end it lasted for about 3 years until 2011. What made me
move on was reading <a href="https://pragprog.com/titles/ahptl/pragmatic-thinking-and-learning/">“Pragmatic Thinking and
Learning”</a>,
which convinced me that it is a good idea to have a personal wiki to organize my
research. One of my colleagues pointed me to DokuWiki, which he described as a
lightweight wiki being solely based on markdown-formatted text files and thus
requiring no database. This convinced me. No database requirement made it easy
to set up, and versatility of configuration made it possible to tweak everything
to my liking. From now on DokuWiki acted both as my official homepage,
containing information for students and my research portfolio, as well as my
personal wiki, which was hidden behind a login. I could now organize all my
research notes into pages and the ease of doing that meant I was now making a
lot more notes than I used to. I also really liked plugin support. One of the
plugins allowed to me have both Polish and English version of each publicly
visible subpage. Another provided LaTeX support, allowing to render formulas
related to wavelet transforms.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-07-12-all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites/dokuwiki_homepage.png"><img src="/images/posts/2023-07-12-all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites/dokuwiki_homepage_thumbnail.png" /></a>
<figcaption>
My old homepage running on DokuWiki.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>While at first I was quite impressed with DokuWiki, over time I realized that it
doesn’t quite live up to the promise of its storage being entirely text based.
While the current content of all the pages is indeed stored in text files, under
the hood DokuWiki maintains history of all the edits (after all, it is designed
to host a wiki) as well as an elaborate system of all sorts of caches and
indices. This means that editing the text files directly instead of using the
HTML editor can potentially get you into trouble with internal data consistency.
And while above I stated how DokuWiki made it easy to make notes, over time my
workflow evolved towards being terminal-based and at this point using a separate
browser-embedded editor to take notes became a problem. Moreover, all the
caches and historical records are binary files and therefore storing sources of
the website in a version control system was also a bit of a problem.</p>
<p>Lessons learned:</p>
<ul>
<li>Having a personal wiki is a fantastic idea. However, it must be possible to
easily integrate the process of taking notes with the rest of my workflow.
Therefore, HTML editors suck.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="yet-another-lambda-blog">Yet Another Lambda Blog</h2>
<p>When I got into functional programming back in 2012 I thought it would be a
great idea to also run a blog on the topic. Aside from the fact that I enjoy
sharing my knowledge with others, a blog would also serve a similar purpose as
the personal wiki. It would be a place where I can record my knowledge for
future purposes<a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"><sup>3</sup></a>. I have already learned that relying on an external blog
hosting service is not a good idea - I already knew I want full ownership of the
content I create - so I decided to go with self-hosting and set up a blog CMS
along with my homepage on my university’s server. Today I can safely say that
while the assumptions were good, the execution was not: I went with Wordpress.</p>
<p>Wordpress seemed like a good choice due to amount of offered features, both
built-in and available via additional plugins. A variety of themes meant I had
no problem adjusting the looks of the blog to my liking. Similarly to Blogger,
Wordpress offered an online WYSIWYG, which at this point I was still willing to
tolerate. What proved to be the biggest downside was the maintenance burden.
Firstly, since the instance was self-hosted, I was responsible for keeping my
installation up-to-date. Most updates went fine, but some did not and I found
myself spending hours trying to recover from a failed update. An unexpected
obstacle came from my hosting, which turned out to be using an extremely old
release of <a href="https://www.pld-linux.org/">PLD Linux</a> with a woefully out-of-date
PHP version that has not received any security updates for about a decade. At
some point this became a problem since Wordpress bumped their minimal required
PHP version and I was no longer able to update my installation. This is a big
deal. Due to its popularity, Wordpress installations, especially those outdated
ones without security fixes, are a common target for hacker attacks. Moreover,
spambots are a major issue, with spam making up over 99,99% of all comments. In
order to manage this spam you either turn off comments completely or use a
plugin for filtering spam (I used Akismet). Lastly, there’s the issue of
backups. Wordpress has plugins that allow you to backup all of your
installation, but moving contents backed up this way to a different installation
is not a straightforward task. Or at least was not straightforward last time I
tried it - perhaps things have improved?</p>
<p>Overall, using a self-hosted Wordpress installation was a major pain with lots
of time spent on maintenance. Even though I now owned all the content I
created, the fact that it was all stored in a database made it difficult to
backup or migrate.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-07-12-all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites/yalb.png"><img src="/images/posts/2023-07-12-all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites/yalb_thumbnail.png" /></a>
<figcaption>
Yet Another Lambda Blog running on Wordpress.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Lessons learned:</p>
<ul>
<li>Self-hosting a large CMS is difficult and time consuming.</li>
<li>Database is a major source of problems.</li>
<li>Comment system is a major source of pain.</li>
<li>Blogging is still fun.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="cyberbrain4-gollum-based-personal-wiki">Cyberbrain<a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4" role="doc-noteref"><sup>4</sup></a>: gollum-based personal wiki</h2>
<p>At some point I have found myself no longer using my personal wiki. It’s not
that I stopped using it suddenly. It just happened gradually over time. This
really surprised me, since a personal wiki is a Good Thing and many times have I
been grateful for taking the time to write down various things that I’ve
learned. After thinking about it for a while I realized the cause: I really
hated the online interface. It was slow and completely disconnected from my
workflow: I spent 90% of my work time in the terminal, using Emacs in text mode
as my editor. Making notes in the wiki meant switching to the browser and using
a completely different way of editing text than the one I use normally. This
was too heavyweight and requires too large a context switch.</p>
<p>The solution to this problem came in the form of
<a href="https://github.com/gollum/gollum/">gollum</a>. Gollum is a markdown based wiki
engine that can run as a local service on my machine. And this time “markdown
based” really means what it means - no weird caching or indexing like in
DokuWiki. Gollum requires that the wiki is stored in a git repository and as
such all history is recorded outside of the wiki engine itself. In fact, most
of you have likely already seen gollum in action as it is the engine that was
originally created to power GitHub wikis<a href="#fn5" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref5" role="doc-noteref"><sup>5</sup></a>. Multiple markdown flavours are
supported, but the DokuWiki one isn’t, so I had to migrate all notes I already
had on my personal wiki.</p>
<p>Once migration was done I had a perfect wiki. All my notes are now stored in
Markdown files (GitHub Markdown with minor tweaks and enhancements) organized in
directories. Since it’s Markdown it is easy to edit in Emacs, which allows me
to seamlessly integrate taking notes with programming. In fact, for most of the
time I view my notes in Emacs. I switch to a web browser view of the wiki only
when I need to retrieve information which location in the wiki I am unsure of
and I need to click through several pages in order to find it. This doesn’t
happen too often since I try to keep my wiki organized. At the moment all my
notes total at 1.5MB - and that’s just text-based Markdown files, excluding any
multimedia or git history - so it is crucial that they are all well structured.
Moreover, storing everything in a git repository is now not only a natural thing
to do, but in fact mandatory. To simplify my workflow with the wiki even
further I created a <code>Makefile</code> with following contents:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1"><pre class="sourceCode makefile"><code class="sourceCode makefile"><span id="cb1-1"><a href="#cb1-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="dv">all:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-2"><a href="#cb1-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>       git add .</span>
<span id="cb1-3"><a href="#cb1-3" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>       git commit -m <span class="st">&quot;Local changes (via Makefile)&quot;</span> || exit 0</span>
<span id="cb1-4"><a href="#cb1-4" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a></span>
<span id="cb1-5"><a href="#cb1-5" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="ot">.PHONY:</span><span class="dt"> all</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>which allows me to commit all changes to my wiki by pressing F8 in Emacs.
Granted, the commit message is not descriptive, but in all honesty I don’t think
I ever found myself referring to my wiki’s history.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-07-12-all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites/gollum.png"><img src="/images/posts/2023-07-12-all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites/gollum_thumbnail.png" /></a>
<figcaption>
My new personal wiki running on local instance of gollum.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Lessons learned:</p>
<ul>
<li>Personal wiki is essential for a programmer.</li>
<li>For a personal wiki it suffices to have it hosted locally.</li>
<li>Markdown is a good and lightweight way of taking notes.</li>
<li>It is important to minimize context switch between doing productive work and
taking notes.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="professional-homepage-with-a-blog-version-3-hakyll-github-pages">Professional homepage with a blog, version 3: Hakyll + GitHub pages</h2>
<p>After switching to gollum I was still using DokuWiki to run my professional
homepage. That page, as well as Wordpress-based Yet Another Lambda Blog, came
to an end in 2021. After spending 13 years at my University I decided to change
jobs, which meant losing access to my hosting. I had to migrate everything
somewhere else.</p>
<p>All my experiences so far lead me to one conclusion: the simpler the better. I
didn’t want anything that uses a database. I didn’t want a comment system. I
wanted to store everything in a simple text-based format that is easy to migrate
and store in a git repository. This left me with two choices: either plain
HTML+CSS or a Markdown-based solution. I wasn’t yet ready to return to using
HTML. After considering my options I decided to go with
<a href="https://jaspervdj.be/hakyll/">Hakyll</a>, a static HTML generator inspired by
Jekyll, but written in Haskell.</p>
<p>I wanted to combine my professional homepage with a blog. This meant migrating
already existing DokuWiki pages, which was simple since I already knew how to
handle this from earlier migration to gollum, but it also meant migrating from
Wordpress to Markdown. This was a bigger problem, but luckily I found a tool
that did 90% of the job of converting existing blog posts to Markdown. There
were still cleanups and tweaks here and there, in particular when it came to
images and footnotes. The process was tedious but overall not that long.</p>
<p>There was a bunch of other stuff that had to be set up in Hakyll, from RSS feed
to creating templates and metadata for blog pages, and various rules defining
how and where to put various files (in particular images). Luckily, Hakyll
documentation and online examples were helpful, and after about a week of work
the migration was complete. You are most likely viewing the result right now,
but in case another migration happens in the future here’s a screenshot:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-07-12-all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites/hakyll.png"><img src="/images/posts/2023-07-12-all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites/hakyll_thumbnail.png" /></a>
<figcaption>
Current homepage and blog built with Hakyll.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Overall, once setup Hakyll is easy to use and does the job. It still has its
downsides though. Firstly, it is a rather heavyweight technology in a sense
that it requires full Haskell toolchain to be installed in the system, plus a
bunch of library dependencies. I am a Haskell programmer so I tend to have
Haskell compiler at hand, but this is no small requirement. And being
Markdown-based leads to limitations that you’re going to hit sooner or later.
For me this happened when I decided I want to have captioned images that can be
enlarged with a click. To achieve the desired effect I had to mix HTML with
Markdown and write some extra CSS to ensure images display correctly on mobile
devices. So whenever I want to insert an image I have to write something like
this:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb2"><pre class="sourceCode html"><code class="sourceCode html"><span id="cb2-1"><a href="#cb2-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="kw">&lt;div</span> <span class="er">class</span><span class="ot">=</span><span class="st">&quot;thumbnail&quot;</span><span class="kw">&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb2-2"><a href="#cb2-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="kw">&lt;figure&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb2-3"><a href="#cb2-3" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>[![](/images/posts/2023-07-12-all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites/hakyll_thumbnail.png)](/images/posts/2023-07-12-all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites/hakyll.png)</span>
<span id="cb2-4"><a href="#cb2-4" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="kw">&lt;figcaption&gt;</span>Current homepage and blog built with Hakyll.<span class="kw">&lt;/figcaption&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb2-5"><a href="#cb2-5" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="kw">&lt;/figure&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb2-6"><a href="#cb2-6" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="kw">&lt;/div&gt;</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>Lessons learned:</p>
<ul>
<li>Static site generation is great.</li>
<li>Markdown is good enough for basic formatting, but sooner or later you hit
its limitations.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="what-next">What next?</h2>
<p>At the moment the only active web page that I maintain is this blog running on
Hakyll. Once set up it is easy to work with and allows me to do everything I
need. That being said, I am not happy about Hakyll’s weight, in particular its
dependence on a plethora of Haskell libraries. It was trivially simple to bring
Fremen Zone back to life after two decades of no maintenance. Will it be
equally easy to restore this blog in two decades time? I have serious doubts
about that, but nevertheless have no intention of migrating to anything else.
For now.</p>
<p>Restoring the Fremen Zone back to life sparked a new desire in me. While I said
I have no intention of updating it, I feel like re-doing the whole site from
scratch. All the reviews on the page were written from a perspective of a
teenager. Today, being middle-aged, I view most of things surprisingly
similarly, but would definitely make a better choice of words in expressing
myself. And so I am slowly gathering material for a new Dune fanpage. All the
lessons above have taught me to avoid complexity and stay as close to the basics
as possible. And so my plan is to create a new website based on pure HTML and
CSS. This will take some learning effort. I haven’t used these technologies in
a while and they have evolved in the past two decades, in particular when it
comes to handling mobile devices. My experience with creating Fremen Zone 20
years ago taught me that creating content is a time consuming process, and
therefore I am assuming this new website will take years, rather than months, to
complete.</p>
<section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>I think they are still abandonware and there is any legal way of obtaining
them, except for second-hand market.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Official English translations of “Politechnika Łódzka” changed over time.
When I started my work it was Technical University of Lodz but sometime
around 2013, I think, it changed to Lodz University of Technology.<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>I can’t overstate how good a thing this is. I have revisited some of my
blog entries and found them extremely helpful and was grateful to myself
that I took the time to write them.<a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>The term “cyberbrain” comes from Ghost in the Shell and refers to
cybernetic brain replacements used in the manga and its anime adaptation.<a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>I am not sure whether this is still the case. Based on bits and pieces of
information I was able to find on the Internet I think gollum and the
engine that currently powers GitHub wikis are technically separate
codebases, but gollum strives to remain fully compatible with GitHub.<a href="#fnref5" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>12/07/2023</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-07-12-all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>More GameBoy modding</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 05/06/2023
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="more-gameboy-modding">More GameBoy modding</h1>
<p>Since my <a href="2023-01-23-gameboy-color-nes-themed-modkit-from-funnyplaying.html">previous post about modding a GameBoy
Color</a>, back
in January, I have modded three more GameBoys: a GameBoy Pocket, an original
GameBoy DMG, and a GameBoy Advance. I want to talk about the first two today,
leaving the third one for later.</p>
<h2 id="gameboy-pocket">GameBoy Pocket</h2>
<p>I already have one modded GameBoy Pocket, but I wanted to make another one for
my wife. I got a donor GBP with a damaged screen that had a wide black stripe
running from top to bottom of the screen.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_donor.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_donor_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Donor GameBoy Pocket next to a new shell.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Modding GBP is very similar to GBC, so it went pretty smooth. Similarly to GBC,
I trimmed the cartridge slot pins and secured them with Kapton tape.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_trimmed_pins.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_trimmed_pins_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Cartridge slot pins trimmed and secured.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>When I was making the NES-themed GBC I reported how replacing the speaker with a
new one resulted in no sound. I don’t know why that was the case but back then
I just restored the old speaker. I decided to try using remaining replacement
speaker in this build and it worked without any problems. I have no clue what I
did wrong with the GBC.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_new_speaker.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_new_speaker_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
New speaker installed.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>When installing the screen I always have a dilemma whether to use the provided
3M dust seal. A supposed advantage of using it is that it should provide
protection against dust getting between the screen and the lens<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a>. A clear
disadvantage is that once the screen is glued to the seal it cannot be removed
without being destroyed. It also cannot be even adjusted in any way. After some
deliberation I decided to install the dust seal, which required cutting small
fragments on the side so that it fits in the shell.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_dust_seal_1.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_dust_seal_1_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Dust seal required some cutting to fit the shell.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_dust_seal_2.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_dust_seal_2_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Dust seal in place.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And here’s the lens and the screen already installed:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_screen_installed.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_screen_installed_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_lens_installed.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_lens_installed_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Finally, there’s some more soldering required. One contact on the ribbon cable
must be soldered to the power switch in order to provide enough power for the
screen, while another is used to solder a touch sensor. With these finished I
was ready to assemble the console. Here are a couple of photos of the finished
build.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_front.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_front_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_back.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_back_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Front and back
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_colour_1.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_colour_1_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_colour_2.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/gbp_colour_2_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
IPS panel offers multiple colour schemes.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>One thing that didn’t go quite right is the centring of the screen. The photos
don’t show this well, but the screen is slightly shifted to the left so that the
left edge of the displayed image is covered. And since the screen is now glued
to the dust seal it’s not possible to adjust it. I might decide to fix this one
day at the expense of sacrificing a screen, which are not that expensive.</p>
<h2 id="gameboy-dmg">GameBoy DMG</h2>
<p>I also have one modded GameBoy DMG in my collection. Shortly before returning
from the UK to Poland I bought it from eBay with all mods already installed. I
knew GameBoys will be harder to find in Poland - well, not really harder to
find, just more expensive - so I decided to get one that’s already modded since
I didn’t have the time to mod it myself. However, I wasn’t entirely happy with
how that GameBoy looks. I could have just replaced the shell with a new one,
but I figured it would be more fun to get a new GameBoy DMG and mod it myself.
As expected, GameBoys in Poland are expensive so I got one from Sweden since it
was cheaper (sic!). The unit was sold as faulty/not working, but I don’t really
believe in such a thing as a broken GameBoy. There is a GameBoy that literally
<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/mildlyinteresting/comments/8ifqbp/gameboy_at_nintendo_nyc_store_damaged_in_bombing/">survived a bombing during the Gulf War and it still
works</a>.
I assume there is simply no way that a DMG can’t be fixed.</p>
<p>When the unit arrived it had a missing lens, damage on the screen, and signs of
spilled acid in the battery compartment.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_before.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_before_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Looks like this DMG went through a lot.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I put in the batteries and - surprise, surprise - it didn’t power on. Well, the
seller wasn’t lying. I thought this must have something to do either with
corrosion from spilled batteries or the power switch. My first debugging step
was to check continuity between the battery contacts.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_multimeter.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_multimeter_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Testing battery contacts with a multimeter.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In the photo above my multimeter shows no continuity between the spring and a
metal plate that spring is attached to. Looks like the acid must have gotten
between the plate and the spring causing corrosion. The easiest way to test
whether this is indeed the problem was transferring the main board to a new
shell.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_testing_main_board.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_testing_main_board_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Main board placed in a new shell.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I inserted the batteries, turned the console on, and it Just Worked. So the
problem was with the damaged contacts from spilled batteries. I was glad this
went so easily. If the problem was with the power switch this repair would have
gotten much more difficult.</p>
<p>The DMG actually consists of two boards. One is the main board with a CPU -
that’s the one in photo above - while the other connects to the screen and also
contains button contacts. Installing a new IPS panel requires replacing the
other board with a new one. It also requires soldering a speaker and this is
the only soldering required by this mod.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_speaker.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_speaker_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Preparing to solder the speaker.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>With the speaker in place I tested everything to make sure that both the speaker
and the screen work as expected.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_testing.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_testing_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Testing screen and speaker before assembly.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I was now ready to install the screen and the lens, and assemble everything
together. This kit comes with a very nice mounting bracket for the screen. It
fits very tightly, ensuring that the screen is correctly centred. It also
covers components on the ribbon cable so there is no need to secure them with
Kapton tape as I did in my other GameBoys.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_parts.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_parts_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Preparing to install the screen.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_dust_seal.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_dust_seal_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Dust seal in place.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_mounting_bracket.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_mounting_bracket_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Mounting bracket in place.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_boards_connected.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_boards_connected_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Main board and screen board connected with a ribbon cable.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>One minor issue that appeared during the final assembly was insufficient number
of screws to attach the screen and button board to the shell. Eight are
required but the kit came with only six. My solution was to use the screws
from original GameBoy, though these turned out to be slightly too long.</p>
<p>This build was surprisingly quick, taking me less than two hours. I am very
happy with the end result, though as usual top and bottom of the IPS panel stand
out from under the lens and this is clearly visible in a transparent shell. One
other complain I could possibly have with the shell is that it doesn’t have any
Nintendo or GameBoy branding.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_after.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_after_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
My new smoke-black DMG next to already owned white one.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>While doing the final tests I discovered one small issue. With this kit the
contrast wheel is repurposed to adjust screen settings: brightness, colour, and
retro pixel mode. I realized that the wheel doesn’t have enough clearance and
is being pressed against the shell and gets stuck in one position.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_contrast_wheel.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding/dmg_contrast_wheel_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Contrast wheel did not have enough clearance and was getting stuck.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>My conjecture is that the problem is caused by the two missing screws mentioned
above. I used the six screws provided with the kit around the button contacts.
From my experience getting the board to fight tightly around the contacts is
crucial for the buttons to work correctly. Two missing screws that I replaced
using ones from the original unit were placed below the screen. As already
mentioned, these screws were a bit too long and didn’t hold the board as tightly
as screws provided with the kit. My guess is that if the board had a tighter
fight there it wouldn’t press the contrast wheel against the shell and all would
work as expected. My ad-hoc solution was to slightly loosen two of the screws
that hold the shell together. Now the contrast wheel can move freely, while the
shell still remains nicely fitted.</p>
<h2 id="whats-next">What’s next?</h2>
<p>As mentioned at the beginning of this post, I have also modded a GameBoy Advance
using a TFT panel that I have not used before. I want to spend more time
testing it before writing a post about it. I also have a GameBoy Advance SP
waiting to be modded, but for now I can’t find a shell that I would be happy
with, and I can’t decide what kind of screen to use - a TFT panel mentioned
above or a regular IPS panel? Once I do more testing with the TFT panel I
should be able to decide what components I want to use with the SP. Last but
not least, I have a NeoGeo Pocket Color. Recently I managed to buy a flashcart
for it and now the only thing it needs to be really usable is a new screen.
However, modding GBA SP and NGPC might have to wait for a few months due to
financial reasons.</p>
<section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>My primary GameBoy Advance does not have a dust seal and it is yet to get
any dust under the lens.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>05/06/2023</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-06-05-more-gameboy-modding.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Firmament</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-06-03-firmament.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 03/06/2023
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="firmament">Firmament</h1>
<p>I have quite a lengthy wishlist of computer games I am awaiting to be released.
When one of these games is finally published what typically happens is that I
don’t have the time to play it because, well, adult life. But not this time.
Firmament, a new game by Cyan, was released two weeks ago and I jumped right
into it. Cyan is a studio that’s been around since the late 80s, and when you
think of it this in itself is a remarkable achievement<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a>. They are most
famously known for the Myst series, which I am ashamed to admit I have not
played (yet?). But I did play their previous game, Obduction, and it was
remarkable. I was impatiently awaiting Firmament in hope of getting more of the
same. I finished Firmament today and sadly didn’t exactly get what I was hoping
for, but it definitely wasn’t a bad experience either.</p>
<p>Just like all games made by Cyan, Firmament is a game where you explore
stunningly beautiful worlds, discover their story, and solve environmental
puzzles. In Firmament there are three main Realms. Firstly, mountainous and
icy Curievale:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/curievale_1.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/curievale_1_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/curievale_2.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/curievale_2_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/curievale_3.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/curievale_3_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Then there’s lush St. Andrews with its conservatory:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/st_andrews_1.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/st_andrews_1_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/st_andrews_2.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/st_andrews_2_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/st_andrews_3.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/st_andrews_3_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And rocky Juleston where you’ll find an array of electrical batteries and a
sulphur processing facility:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/juleston_1.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/juleston_1_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/juleston_2.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/juleston_2_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Finally there’s The Swan, a tiny hub world that allows you to travel between the
Realms:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/the_swan.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/the_swan_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Each world also contains an Arch, a sky-reaching metallic construction, as well
as a tower. You play the role of a Keeper and your task will be to raise these
towers from beneath the surface and get to their tops. You do this using a tool
called the Adjunct that allows you to manipulate surrounding environment by
connecting to sockets located on doors, lifts, and other mechanical devices.</p>
<p>Firmament has three core elements that make up the experience. Firstly, there
are the visuals, which wowed me from the first minutes of the game. In case the
screenshots above weren’t enough here are a few more:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/arch_1.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/arch_1_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/interior_1.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/interior_1_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/interior_2.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/interior_2_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/underwater.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/underwater_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/juleston_tower.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/juleston_tower_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<p>One of Cyan’s trademarks is their design of steampunk machines and environments,
and Firmament delivers on that front. However, while all the Realms are
beautiful, they are also quite similar to each other in that they are all worlds
filled with nature and similarly looking devices. This is a huge step back
compared to Obduction, where all the worlds were truly distinct from one
another.</p>
<p>The second element of the experience are puzzles. They form core part of the
gameplay. Unfortunately this is where Firmament should have been a lot better.
There were few puzzles that I really liked: ones where the rules of the puzzle
and its goal are easy to understand, but the solution itself requires thinking.
Unfortunately, most of the puzzles don’t fall into that category, having all
sorts of design problems. Some puzzles were tedious: I knew the solution but
was forced to walk back and forth to implement it. Others were totally obscure
and I solved them with trial and error. One of the reviews I saw online
compared the puzzles to towers of Hanoi, and that’s an accurate comparison.
Even if I knew what needed to be done, actually doing it often required lots
back and forth attempts. Again, Obduction had much better puzzles, especially
those that required combining elements between various worlds.</p>
<p>The last part of the experience is the plot, and this is what Firmament does
very poorly. In Obduction there was lots of environmental storytelling and many
bits and pieces to put together, allowing to recreate what has actually
happened. Granted, Obduction’s storytelling wasn’t perfect - <a href="https://steamcommunity.com/sharedfiles/filedetails/?id=1186090336">a kind soul went
through the effort of explaining everything for those who got
lost</a> - but
it was much better than what Firmament has to offer. In Firmament the player is
accompanied by Mentor, an avatar who acts as a narrator and tells successive
parts of the story as player progresses through the game. And that’s it.
There’s nothing to be figured out from the environment, nothing for the player
to piece together.</p>
<p>I also have to mention technical problems of Firmament. After the release many
people complained about getting softlocked due to puzzle bugs, or narrator voice
completely disappearing after certain point in the game. I was spared these
issues, but my playthrough was plagued by repeated crashes to desktop:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/crash.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/crash_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
A sadly common sight.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>If I was lucky crash to desktop would happen once an hour. If I was less lucky
I would experience seven crashes in 30 minutes. I reported these bugs to Cyan
support, but to this day these crashes have not been fixed<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a>. They are the
primary reason why it took me 2 weeks to finish a game that ultimately takes
less than 8 hours to play. I also have to mention the menus. While the game
visuals are stunning, the menus look like prototypes that made it into
production:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/menu_1.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/menu_1_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/menu_2.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-06-03-firmament/menu_2_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Menu’s are not the most important thing, but they certainly make for a bad first
impression of the game.</p>
<p>My overall impressions of Firmament are good, but aside from the visuals it
certainly is a step back compared to Obduction. If you haven’t played any game
from Cyan and would like to give it a try, Obduction would definitely be my
recommendation, not Firmament. And if you want to give Firmament a try I
recommend waiting for more bugfixes and a sale.</p>
<section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>I just finished reading Jason Schreier’s book <em>“Press Reset: Ruin and
Recovery in the Video Game Industry”</em> which is exactly on the topic of
game studios getting closed all the time, and often for no good reason.
Great book, highly recommended.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p><strong>15/07/2023 UPDATE:</strong> 1.2 patch for Firmament has just been released and
it is supposed to fix these crashes, though I haven’t tested this myself.<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>03/06/2023</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-06-03-firmament.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>How my new wireless headphones caused me eye problems</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-06-02-how-my-new-wireless-headphones-caused-me-eye-problems.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 02/06/2023
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="how-my-new-wireless-headphones-caused-me-eye-problems">How my new wireless headphones caused me eye problems</h1>
<p>(I know the title of this post looks like a total click-bait, but please bear
with me.)</p>
<p>Nine months ago, in early September 2022, I began experiencing eye problems. My
eyes would become bloodshot, dry, and start itching, sometimes with sharp pain
behind the eyeballs.
<a href="/images/posts/2023-06-02-how-my-new-wireless-headphones-caused-me-eye-problems/right_eye.jpg">Here</a>
is just one photo showing the symptoms.</p>
<p>I work as a programmer, spending at least 8 hours a day in front of a monitor,
so obviously I put a lot of strain on my eyes. But such rapid development of
symptoms was very surprising. Interestingly, there seemed to be no general rule
as to when this would happen. Sometimes I would go to bed without any problems
and wake up in the morning with my eyes hurting. Or I would experience the most
severe symptoms during the weekend when I didn’t spend any time in front of the
screen. Sometimes only one eye would be affected, while the other was fine.
All of this was worrying.</p>
<p>My first attempt at dealing with the problem was using over-the-counter eye
drops available at the pharmacy. I tried these for about 4-5 weeks but when
things did not improve I went to the optometrist. Examination showed no clear
cause of problems and I was prescribed steroid eye drops. These somewhat
alleviated the symptoms, but the problems persisted. I went to another
optometrist to get a second opinion but again everything seemed fine wit my eyes
and there was no obvious cause for the problems I was experiencing. I got some
other medicine, including gel with vitamin A, but these at best temporarily
helped with the symptoms.</p>
<p>My problems started in September. It was January already and the whole thing
was significantly affecting my daily life and general well-being. As an act of
desperation I told everything to my physio. She’s a real genius and in the past
helped me with problems I would never think are musculoskeletal. She began
asking me about any possible changes in my desktop setup: “Have you changed font
size?”, “Is your screen closer or farther than it was?”, “Have you changed your
chair?”, etc. I answered all these questions with “no”. My setup remains
unchanged for the past several years: same chair, same table, same monitor, same
UI settings. Nothing has changed.</p>
<p>Or has it? Two days after talking to her it dawned on me: I have new wireless
headphones. I bought them online so it was easy to check the purchase date:
26th of August. Just a few days before my problems began. Could this be the
problem? I remember first using the headphones they were a bit too tight,
causing my jaw muscle to hurt during the first couple of days. But then the jaw
pain went away and things seemed fine, except I didn’t thought eye problems
could be the caused by headphones. I had to test this hypothesis and, with a
lot of regret, put the headphones away and went back to my old wired earbuds.
From that moment things gradually began to improve. Recovery process wasn’t
immediate. It took several weeks before I could declare my eye problems to be
practically gone.</p>
<p>It seems that my eyes were hurting due to eye muscles being strained, though I
still don’t know what was directly causing this strain. Was it the pressure
from headphones on the jaw muscles or the extra weight placed on my head
straining neck muscles? Either way it looks like I can’t go back to my wireless
headphones. Once the symptoms disappeared I thought I’ll try using my new
headphones again and this time it only took 15 minutes before the characteristic
sharp pain behind my eye reappeared.</p>
<p>I’m sharing this in hope it helps someone who might be struggling with a similar
problem and can’t find the cause. I’m specifically not saying which exact
headphones I got since I think that is completely irrelevant here.</p>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>02/06/2023</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-06-02-how-my-new-wireless-headphones-caused-me-eye-problems.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Installing xStation</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 25/03/2023
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="installing-xstation">Installing xStation</h1>
<center>
<strong>DISCLAIMER:</strong> This post is not intended to serve as installation tutorial.
</center>
<p>When <a href="2022-12-26-recalbox-rgb-dual-some-impressions-after-six-months-of-usage.html">reviewing RGB
Dual</a>
I mentioned how Recalbox struggled with emulating PlayStation (PSX) games.
Although Raspberry Pi should have enough computing power to run PSX games at
full speed, emulator used by Recalbox (SwanStation), is not up to the task.
This was a big disappointment since my primary goal when getting RGB Dual was
being able to run PSX games. This left me with only one choice: buy the
original PlayStation. Luckily, PSX was a popular console so finding one wasn’t
much of a problem. Just like with other retro consoles problems start once you
actually get the hardware since it requires modifications or extra accessories.
Luckily for me I already have an RGB cable and a BlueRetro receiver for PS2, and
these are compatible with PSX allowing me to connect the console to my PVM and
use DualSense controller. I was left with two missing pieces. Firstly, the
memory card. I was lucky and managed to grab MemCard Pro from 8BitmMods<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a>.
This modern memory card replacement allows to store memory card images on an SD
card allowing for easy backup and save transfer between real hardware and
emulators. The second missing piece was an optical drive emulator (ODE), since
running games from original CDs is not feasible these days.</p>
<p>When it comes to PlayStation ODEs there are following options:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://ps-io.com/">PSIO</a>. Connects to expansion port at the back of
console. This is very non-invasive and easy to install, which is a big
plus. Unfortunately, PSIO has been out of stock for the past year if not
longer. Moreover, I’ve seen people complaining a lot about compatibility,
though according to official FAQ PSIO is compatible with 99.5% games. Last
but not least, <a href="https://ps-io.com/blocked-serials/">PSIO seems to be DRMed</a>
and needs to be registered with the manufacturer, which makes it a no-go for
me.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/x-station">xStation</a>. This ODE replaces the original CD
drive of the console. Installation is difficult as it requires precise
soldering. According to the internets xStation offers better compatibility
than PSIO.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://shop.terraonion.com/shop/system/playstation/view">TerraOnion MODE</a>.
MODE was originally developed for Saturn and Dreamcast but now it also works
with PSX. Unfortunately it’s out of stock and requires registration to
receive firmware updates. As a bonus, it’s also quite expensive and runs
games from a hard drive rather than a memory card.</p></li>
<li><p>Bonus: <a href="https://github.com/paulocode/picostation">PicoStation</a>. An open
source alternative to xStation that is based on Raspberry Pi Pico.
Unfortunately it’s still in development so not really an option at this
moment.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>I went with the xStation. As with lots of retro mods these days xStation was
out of stock but luckily the pre-orders were up. I ordered one unit and, after
some delays, finally received it in mid February.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation/1_xstation_kit.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation/1_xstation_kit_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
xStation kit comes in a nice box. QSB (Quick Solder Board) is included with the board.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I already learned it’s a good idea to install console mods during the weekend.
Installation usually takes longer than expected and it was no different this
time. Installation of xStation requires two main steps:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Soldering a QSB (Quick Solder Board) to the motherboard of PlayStation.</li>
<li>Lifting pins on one of the integrated circuits, the IC701.</li>
</ol>
<p>I wasn’t too concerned about the soldering. Lifting pins was the scary part.
It’s something I haven’t done before and something, I imagine, that could easily
go wrong given how small the pins are. Here’s a photo with a coin that’s the
size of a penny coin:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation/2_ic_size.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation/2_ic_size_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
IC701. Several pins of this chip have to be lifted when installing xStation.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Soldering seemingly went smooth. There are around 20 solder points, some of
them requiring uncovering the via pads with a sharp tool (Olfa knife comes in
handy). Having already some soldering experience from the previous mods this
wasn’t too difficult.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation/3_qcb_preparation.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation/3_qcb_preparation_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
QSB secured in place before soldering.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation/4_qcb_done.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation/4_qcb_done_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
QSB soldered to PlayStation motherboard. I’m happy with how cleanly the cable turned out.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Lifting pins also wasn’t as difficult as I imagined. I followed <a href="https://www.youtube.com/live/QC3SAGdNWB8?feature=share&amp;t=3627">Voultar’s
advice</a> and used
a dental pick. Again, things <em>seemingly</em> went smooth.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation/5_pins_lifted.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation/5_pins_lifted_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Lifted pins on IC701.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation/6_lifted_pins_secured.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation/6_lifted_pins_secured_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
I secured the pads with Kapton tape but ended up removing the tape later.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation/7_two_boards.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation/7_two_boards_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Modified motherboard on the left and a spare one on the right.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As you can see in the last photo I have two PlayStation motherboards. Given
that this is a difficult mod I decided to get a spare one in advance. Luckily
it wasn’t necessary, although you will see things didn’t go smooth.</p>
<p>As the final step I installed the xStation board, connecting it with a ribbon
cable, and re-assembled the console:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation/8_assembly.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation/8_assembly_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Putting everything back together.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>After assembling the PlayStation I connected it to the TV, turned it on,
and… got a black screen. Console seemed dead. It was time for hardware
debugging, which is something I don’t have a lot of experience with. Luckily,
<a href="https://github.com/x-station/xstation-issues#pu-18">there are detailed photos for the xStation showing test points on the
motherboard</a>. I took my
multimeter and began testing connectivity. Now, logic dictates that
connectivity should be a transitive property, meaning that if there is current
flow between points A and B, and there is current flow between points B and C
then there is current flow between points A and C. Surprisingly this didn’t
seem to be the case here. I first measured connectivity between all solder
blobs and their corresponding pins in the ribbon cable slot, and found no
problems. Then I measured connectivity between solder blobs and test points on
the motherboard. Again, no problems here. But then I began measuring
connectivity directly between the ribbon cable slot pins and test points on the
motherboard, and clearly in four cases there was no connectivity. This caused a
lot of head scratching on my side, but I finally figured it out. Apparently
some solder blobs didn’t make connection with their corresponding solder point
on the motherboard, but pushing the blob down with a probe during measurement
made them connect, resulting in connectivity being reported incorrectly. I
re-soldered those four points, measured everything again, and this time all pins
showed as being correctly connected. It was time to re-assemble the console and
test again. This time it did power on and boot into console BIOS.</p>
<p>This was progress, but it was still wrong, since the console should have booted
into xStation menu. Time for another debugging session. This time I went to
Discord and was lucky to be assisted by the creator of xStation. We went
through <em>lots</em> of test, including measuring resistance between points on
PlayStation motherboard and xStation SoC. The diagnosis was that, while
xStation seems to power on and work, data isn’t being transmitted between the SD
card and the console. At this point I’ve been working on xStation for 7 hours,
with most of time being spent on debugging. I was exhausted and ready to call
it a day, but decided to try one last thing. What concerned me from the
beginning was the pin lifting on the IC701. I feared that this is where I went
wrong by accidentally breaking a solder point between the motherboard and one of
the pins that should not have been lifted. This, luckily, has an easy fix. I
took my soldering iron with K tip (large tip resembling a chisel or a scalpel)
and reflowed the remaining pins on IC701. And this did the job! After yet
another re-assembly of the console xStation booted correctly:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation/9_test.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation/9_test_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
After nearly 8 hours of work xStation finally works.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I copied a game image to an SD card, plugged it into xStation to make sure it
indeed works, and finally my work was done. I started at noon and finished
right before 8PM. This was way longer than expected. Note that the above
account is an abridged one. In fact, there was some trial and error when fixing
the solder points on the QSB and I ended up disassembling and reassembling the
console around 7 times or so. Lessons learned:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Practice soldering more.</li>
<li>When lifting pins reflow the remaining ones just in case.</li>
</ol>
<section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>The luck part is in that it was available. In the past 2-3 years
overwhelming majority of mods is notoriously out of stock.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>25/03/2023</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-03-35-installing-xstation.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Free IPS Patcher</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-03-02-free-ips-patcher.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 02/03/2023
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="free-ips-patcher">Free IPS Patcher</h1>
<p>I recently started playing Final Fantasy IV on SNES. Before playing the game I
decided to patch the ROM with <a href="https://www.romhacking.net/hacks/2337/">Namingway Edition
patch</a> and once again found myself
without a tool for applying IPS patches. Sure, there are <a href="https://bbbradsmith.github.io/ipstool/">online
patchers</a> but I hate resorting to online
services for doing such simple tasks. Luckily <a href="https://zerosoft.zophar.net/ips.php">IPS file format is actually very
simple</a> so I decided to write a patching
tool. Behold <a href="https://bitbucket.org/jstolarek/free-ips-patcher">Free IPS
Patcher</a>. Use it from the
command line like so:</p>
<pre><code>ips ROM_FILE PATCH_FILE OUTPUT_FILE</code></pre>
<p>It’s all coded in less than 200 lines of C, with majority of the code being
error handling. I was tempted to write the program in Haskell but I wanted it
to be easily accessible and lets face it, most people don’t have Haskell
toolchain on their machines.</p>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>02/03/2023</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-03-02-free-ips-patcher.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Getting a Sony PVM</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-02-20-getting-a-sony-pvm.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 20/02/2023
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="getting-a-sony-pvm">Getting a Sony PVM</h1>
<p>PVM, standing for “Professional Video Monitor”, is a series of CRT monitors that
were produced by Sony for professional applications, primarily for use in
hospitals and TV studios. PVM production ended in the noughties and they have
since been replaced by LCD monitors, PVMs being then treated as junk and often
scrapped. But in recent years PVMs have been re-discovered by retro enthusiasts
as great monitors for use with consoles that output analogue RGB video signal
(roughly fourth to sixth generation of consoles). This is due to superb image
quality offered by PVMs. After all these were professional monitors equipped
with electronics whose quality was way above consumer grade TV sets.</p>
<p>In early 2023 I finally managed get a Sony PVM, which has been my dream for the
past three years. There were three main obstacles to overcome in order to make
this happen. Firstly, finding a good quality PVM. These monitors are now
around two decades old and many units have developed faults such as burn-ins on
the screen, geometry faults, etc. Secondly, the supply is short and the demand
is high which means that prices have gotten quite high. Thirdly, and this will
be trivial, a 20″ PVM weights 30 kilograms and I don’t have a car, making
transport from another city a logistical nightmare. Luckily for me the stars
aligned in December 2022 and I found a PVM-20M2MDE that was in good condition,
at an acceptable price (still expensive, but it was a price I could afford), and
in a city where I could make a return trip directly by train in one day.
Transporting a 30kg CRT by train turned out to be quite an ordeal but it was
definitely worth it.</p>
<p>Here are some photos comparing Super Metroid on Panasonic TX-21S1TCP and
PVM-20M2MDE:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-02-20-getting-a-sony-pvm/super_metroid.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-02-20-getting-a-sony-pvm/super_metroid_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Super Metroid on Panasonic TV (left) and PVM (right). Click to enlarge.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The difference in image quality is noticeable immediately, especially when you
look at background details, though admittedly colours on the PVM are not as
lively. Here are some closeups:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-02-20-getting-a-sony-pvm/samus.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-02-20-getting-a-sony-pvm/samus_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Samus closeup. Panasonic TV (left) and PVM (right). Click to enlarge.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-02-20-getting-a-sony-pvm/map.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-02-20-getting-a-sony-pvm/map_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Detail closeup. Panasonic TV (top) and PVM (bottom). Click to enlarge.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-02-20-getting-a-sony-pvm/energy.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-02-20-getting-a-sony-pvm/energy_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Detail closeup. Panasonic TV (top) and PVM (bottom). Click to enlarge.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Unfortunately, PVM’s picture quality isn’t perfect due to convergence problems,
which manifest primarily at the edges of the screen. You can notice this by
looking at the “Energy” text on the photo above and observing how the white
letters actually bleed red colour. (They also bleed blue, but since there’s a
1-pixel blue outline around the font you won’t notice it.) This colour bleeding
can be fixed but requires disassembling the monitor and adjusting convergence
rings on the yoke while the monitor is turned on. Voltage inside a PVM (or any
other CRT) can go as high as several kilovolts, so this requires knowledge in
order to do it safely. Luckily, Steve from
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/@RetroTechUSA">RetroTech</a> has lots of good videos on
servicing PVMs and my plan is to go through them and do the convergence
adjustments once I feel confident I won’t hurt myself or screw up the monitor.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-02-20-getting-a-sony-pvm/castlevania.gif"><img src="/images/posts/2023-02-20-getting-a-sony-pvm/castlevania.gif" /></a>
<figcaption>
Castlevania: Symphony of the Night on Sony PVM.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>P.S. Aside from gaming, I found the PVM to be great for watching old anime in
4:3 aspect ratio. At the moment I’m finishing 2nd season of Initial D.</p>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>20/02/2023</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-02-20-getting-a-sony-pvm.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
