<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>Yet Another Lambda Blog</title>
        <link>https://jstolarek.github.io</link>
        <description><![CDATA[A language that doesn't affect the way you think about programming, is not worth knowing]]></description>
        <atom:link href="https://jstolarek.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Goodbye, Google&#58; Switching from GMail to Mailbox</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2024-12-03-goodbye-google-switching-from-gmail-to-mailbox.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 03/12/2024
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="goodbye-google-switching-from-gmail-to-mailbox">Goodbye, Google: Switching from GMail to Mailbox</h1>
<p>In recent years, I have been making attempts to minimize using services provided
by Google, the primary concern being privacy. In my <a href="2024-09-27-goodbye-google-switching-from-google-search-to-kagi.html">earlier
post</a>, I
wrote about using <a href="https://www.kagi.com">Kagi</a> as my search engine of choice.
Today, I want to talk about <a href="https://mailbox.org/">Mailbox.org</a>, a paid email
provider that I migrated to from GMail.</p>
<h2 id="my-expectations-and-why-previous-email-providers-didnt-meet-them">My expectations and why previous email providers didn’t meet them</h2>
<p>I heavily rely on email in my daily life. I always had at least two accounts: a
private one and a professional one at my current workplace. Most of the time, I
had more than one mailbox for work. In order to manage multiple email accounts
conveniently, I use a desktop email client. Thus, a basic requirement for me is
that an email provider allows reading and sending emails via a client. This
sounds like a really, really trivial requirement, but you will see in a moment
that for some email providers this is far from obvious.</p>
<p>For the most part of the last 25 years, I have used a free email account from
<a href="https://www.onet.pl">Onet</a>, a Polish news portal and email provider - think
Yahoo. It being free came at a price of receiving advertising emails directly
to the inbox. Luckily, it is trivial to filter out such mails with a custom
filter in the email client and never see those adds. As such, I was happy with
services provided by Onet. However, at some point they started to silently put
restrictions on emails send via desktop clients. In particular, sending emails
that only contained links or attachments, or were simply too short, resulted in
them being silently dropped by the SMTP server. Imagine a situation where you
are making arrangements with someone and reply simply with “Yes”, and that email
gets silently dropped and never makes it to the other person. Or you just want
to send someone a link, but that person never receives it. I have been in
multiple such situations without realizing it. Dropping emails for no good
reason would be bad enough in itself. But doing so silently in such a way that
the sender does not even know that the message was not delivered is simply too
much. When I realized what is going on, and verified with the provider that
this is an intended behaviour that’s part of their “security policy” (sic!), I
knew I have to start looking for a new email service.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, at this point in time, I was heavily occupied with events in my
private life and did not have the time to properly research paid alternatives.
And so I went with an easily available solution: GMail. Well, that was a
mistake. Firstly, GMail complicates usage of clients that don’t support OAuth
(mine doesn’t). Secondly, GMail places sent emails in the inbox. If you send
an email via a client, your client will then download that email into your
inbox, showing it as a new email. This is a major annoyance. Again, it can be
sorted out with some extra work and custom filters, but this is not how email
should work.</p>
<p>I lived with GMail annoyances for a couple of years, until last November I
finally decided to bite the bullet and move to a new email provider.</p>
<h2 id="mailbox.org-pros-and-cons">Mailbox.org: Pros and Cons</h2>
<p>After some research, and recommendations from friends, I decided on
<a href="https://mailbox.org/">Mailbox.org</a>, which offers a good set of features at a
competitive price. As mentioned earlier, one of my motivations to move away
from Google are privacy concerns. Mailbox.org operates from Germany, which
means it must follow the EU’s strict data protection laws. To me, this was an
important argument in favour of using Mailbox.org.</p>
<p>Mailbox.org offers lots of neat little features that one does not typically get
from free email providers such as GMail. These include multiple email aliases,
disposable addresses, encryption support, detailed SPAM protection settings, and
mailbox backups, among others. Aside from email, Mailbox.org also provides a
suite of online applications. These include:</p>
<ul>
<li>An address book and calendar.</li>
<li>A TODO list that allows to manage tasks, track their progress, set
deadlines, attach files, etc. I couldn’t figure out a way to integrate it
with a calendar, but I admit I haven’t tried very hard. Perhaps there’s a
way of doing it.</li>
<li>Cloud storage with 5GB of space (in the Standard plan).</li>
<li>XMPP chat</li>
<li>Video conferencing based on <a href="https://opentalk.eu">OpenTalk</a>.</li>
<li>Etherpad, a lightweight alternative to Google Docs.</li>
<li>Creating polls and event scheduling based on
<a href="https://framadate.org">Framadate</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>It is good to see alternatives to GSuite finally being offered, though I admit I
have not tested most of these tools, since I rarely collaborate with others via
such tools and tend to work on the desktop. I only really tried using Etherpad
and, frankly speaking, the experience wasn’t great. Firstly, Etherpad seems to
forget which edits were made by whom, i.e. rather than associating edits with a
Mailbox.org account it seems to be using cookies that have short expiration
dates. Secondly, it frequently resets to default display settings, which is
quite annoying - presumably cookies, again. But worst of all, it isn’t
reliable. I had a situation where a document I shared with someone became
completely broken and unresponsive. After contacting the support, I was told
that they had an infrastructure problem and the only way to solve the problem is
to create a new document and copy the contents of the broken document there. It
was a one-time incident, but something like this should not ever happen if the
tool is to be considered reliable.</p>
<p>Beyond that, Mailbox.org offers <a href="https://kb.mailbox.org/en/private/">good technical
documentation</a> - and I really mean that.
This documentation does not shy away from providing full technical details so
that a knowledgeable user gets all the information they need.</p>
<p>And lastly, the service works with an email client without any problems. This
should be obvious, but as demonstrated by my experiences, it isn’t always the
case.</p>
<p>There are a couple of cons, though, aside from the already mentioned Etherpad
incident. Possibly the biggest usability issue are strict SPAM filters. By
“strict” I mean following all sorts of standards, that many big providers on the
internet (such as Microsoft) don’t follow. As a result, some incoming emails
don’t get delivered or arrive delayed. In particular, I have found
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greylisting_(email)">greylisting</a> to cause
trouble. Thankfully, SPAM filter behaviour can be modified in the settings, but
I don’t like how the default settings are problematic, even if, strictly
speaking, the fault does not lie with Mailbox.org.</p>
<p>Mailbox.org offers online technical support - which in itself is good and yet
another thing one does not get with free email services - but I have found that
support to be highly incompetent. I contacted support on three different
occasions, and each experience was bad. I encountered consultants that were
arrogant or lacked knowledge, trying to convince me that the behaviour I am
experiencing is a problem caused by my browser and sending me through many
pointless debugging steps, only to admit in the end that this is actually an
intended behaviour of the service.</p>
<p>Speaking of “intended behaviours of the service”, one of them is repeatedly
logging out of the web client. Not that I use the web client frequently, but
having to log in every other day was annoying when I first started using the
service and frequently experimented with various settings. I initially thought
that this was a bug, since the settings allow to disable automatic logout, but I
was eventually told that this is all intentional - despite what the settings
seem to imply.</p>
<p>There are a few more minor annoyances in the web client, such as the inability
to click any links in emails moved to the SPAM folder. So if you want to click
an unsubscribe link you first need to move an email to the inbox folder, click
the link, and move it back to spam. But again, this isn’t really a huge problem
for me.</p>
<p>One last issue is a really minor one, but when I initially got the new email
address I kept mistaking the <code>.org</code> domain with <code>.com</code> and on several occasions
nearly provided an incorrect email address.</p>
<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>After many years of struggling with free email providers, I finally have a
mailbox that works like it should. I regret not making this move earlier, and I
regret even more ever getting involved with GMail. This was a mistake that I
should not have done, given how hard it is to entirely phase out an old email
address.</p>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>03/12/2024</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2024-12-03-goodbye-google-switching-from-gmail-to-mailbox.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Japanese Video Game Obscurities.  Book review</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2024-12-02-japanese-video-game-obscurities-book-review.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 02/12/2024
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="japanese-video-game-obscurities.-book-review">Japanese Video Game Obscurities. Book review</h1>
<p>In the past couple of months I have been indulging in buying all sorts of retro
stuff from Japan, mostly artbooks, laserdiscs and games. Though I don’t
understand Japanese, at least to an extent that would allow me to fully enjoy
purchased goods, I thought it would be nice to have Japanese releases of some of
my favourite games. The primary motivation is that European and US editions
tend to be prohibitively expensive these days, whereas releases from Japan tend
to be rather cheap - quite understandably, given the language barrier.</p>
<p>While browsing shopping sites for retro games - I happen to have an NTSC-J
version of Sega Saturn - I often run into obscure games that were never released
outside of Japan. Typically, I then search online for information on what these
unknown games even are. A page that comes up very frequently in search results
is <a href="http://www.hardcoregaming101.net/">Hardcore Gaming 101</a>, which seems to
specialize in all sorts of niche games from all eras. I was then very pleased
to learn that Hardcore Gaming 101 also publishes books, one of them being
<a href="http://www.hardcoregaming101.net/books/hg101-presents-japanese-video-game-obscurities/">“Japanese Video Game
Obscurities”</a>
by Kurt Kalata, published in 2019. Once I learned of its existence, I knew I
need to have it.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-12-02-japanese-video-game-obscurities-book-review/cover.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-12-02-japanese-video-game-obscurities-book-review/cover_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The book contains reviews of 101 games, the majority of which were not
officially released outside of Japan. The focus is on retro titles for both
consoles and PCs, with most of the reviewed games being released in the 90s, but
also some titles from 80s and 2000s. Reviews are grouped into chapters by
genre, with each review taking two pages: one page for the review itself and one
for the screenshots.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-12-02-japanese-video-game-obscurities-book-review/princess_crown.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-12-02-japanese-video-game-obscurities-book-review/princess_crown_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-12-02-japanese-video-game-obscurities-book-review/ore_no_shikabane.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-12-02-japanese-video-game-obscurities-book-review/ore_no_shikabane_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-12-02-japanese-video-game-obscurities-book-review/chaos_seed.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-12-02-japanese-video-game-obscurities-book-review/chaos_seed_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-12-02-japanese-video-game-obscurities-book-review/jesus.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-12-02-japanese-video-game-obscurities-book-review/jesus_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-12-02-japanese-video-game-obscurities-book-review/mizzurna_falls.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-12-02-japanese-video-game-obscurities-book-review/mizzurna_falls_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-12-02-japanese-video-game-obscurities-book-review/love_and_destroy.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-12-02-japanese-video-game-obscurities-book-review/love_and_destroy_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-12-02-japanese-video-game-obscurities-book-review/suzuki_bakuhatsu.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-12-02-japanese-video-game-obscurities-book-review/suzuki_bakuhatsu_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As you can see in the photos above, the reviews are short, yet they are
unbelievably succinct. In just a few paragraphs of text, they convey
surprisingly large amounts of information and insight, both about the game
itself and the context surrounding it. Each review offers multiple trails of
further research, typically on the studio’s previous and future titles, similar
games, and artists involved.</p>
<p>If you are interested in retro gaming and enjoy learning about games that didn’t
make it to the West, then “Japanese Video Game Obscurities” is a must-read. It
is well researched, writing is top quality, and choice of screenshots is very
good. The only real complaint I have about the book is the lack of an
alphabetic index of titles, forcing the reader to search the (non-alphabetic)
table of contents when looking for a particular game. Also, the illustration on
the cover looks quite amateurish. That’s not a serious complaint, though
— just don’t let the cover mislead you.</p>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>02/12/2024</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2024-12-02-japanese-video-game-obscurities-book-review.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Goodbye, Google&#58; Switching from Google Search to Kagi</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2024-09-27-goodbye-google-switching-from-google-search-to-kagi.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 27/09/2024
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="goodbye-google-switching-from-google-search-to-kagi">Goodbye, Google: Switching from Google Search to Kagi</h1>
<p>Last year, I wrote about <a href="2023-10-09-lineageos-on-samsung-s7-an-experience-report.html">my experience of installing LineageOS on my
smartphone</a>. The
goal was to have an Android phone that is free of Google spyware. Since then, I
have been gradually moving away from using services provided by Google,
primarily the search engine and email services. In this post, I want to write
about <a href="https://kagi.com/">Kagi</a>, a search engine that I’ve been using since last
October.</p>
<p>Whatever product is being offered on the market, it is crucial that its
customers are satisfied and willing to pay for it. The problem with Google
Search is that its users, i.e. people using Google to find information on the
Internet, are not its customers. It is the advertisers that pay Google for
their service of positioning the ads. And so, search results provided by Google
must first and foremost benefit the advertisers, with the user experience being
a secondary matter. This is nothing new. The problem has been anticipated by
Google creators Sergey Brin and Lawrence Page in their 1998 paper<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The goals of the advertising business model do not always correspond to
providing quality search to users. (…) we expect that advertising funded
search engines will be inherently biased towards the advertisers and away from
the needs of the consumers.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the past years, this has been the subject of a wide discussion sparked by the
gradual degradation of Google’s search results quality.</p>
<p>For a couple of years now, I have not been using Google as my primary search
engine. I switched to DuckDuckGo instead. For the most time, DuckDuckGo worked
well for me, but every now and then it couldn’t find what I was looking for, and
I had to use Google as a fallback.</p>
<h2 id="better-search-results">Better search results</h2>
<p>About a year ago, I heard about Kagi, a new search engine that people have been
raving about. Long story short, I decided to give it a try. Since then, Kagi
has improved my web searching experience by offering better results than its
competitors. No more falling back to Google or DuckDuckGo.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-09-27-goodbye-google-switching-from-google-search-to-kagi/kagi_main.png"><img src="/images/posts/2024-09-27-goodbye-google-switching-from-google-search-to-kagi/kagi_main.png" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The first couple of weeks of using Kagi felt… strange. The search results were
sometimes so accurate that they felt scary. Here’s an example. In a <a href="2024-08-21-fremen-zone-creating-a-website-using-only-html-and-css.html">recent
post about my fan website Fremen
Zone</a>, I
mentioned setting up GitHub actions to validate HTML. I used
<a href="https://github.com/Cyb3r-Jak3/html5validator-action">html5validator-action</a> for
this. I initially ran into a setup problem, where every run of the action
resulted in “There is no git repository detected” error. And so I used Kagi to
search for “Github actions Error: There is no git respository detected” (yes,
there’s a typo in the search phrase). Here is the search result I got from
Kagi:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-09-27-goodbye-google-switching-from-google-search-to-kagi/kagi_win.png"><img src="/images/posts/2024-09-27-goodbye-google-switching-from-google-search-to-kagi/kagi_win.png" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The first result is literally a bug report for the project I was using with the
exact same problem I was facing. It doesn’t get any more accurate than that.
By contrast, here are results for the same search phrase from Google:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-09-27-goodbye-google-switching-from-google-search-to-kagi/google_fail.png"><img src="/images/posts/2024-09-27-goodbye-google-switching-from-google-search-to-kagi/google_fail.png" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And from DuckDuckGo:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-09-27-goodbye-google-switching-from-google-search-to-kagi/ddg_fail.png"><img src="/images/posts/2024-09-27-goodbye-google-switching-from-google-search-to-kagi/ddg_fail.png" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Neither of these results was helpful in any way<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a>. This is just one example,
but this happened over and over again.</p>
<h2 id="is-paying-for-a-search-engine-worth-it">Is paying for a search engine worth it?</h2>
<p>Let’s get this one out of the way: Kagi is a paid service. It gives up entirely
on the ad-based business model, requiring the users to pay with real money and
not their private data. The question is, whether it is worth to pay for a
service that everyone else offers for free?</p>
<p>After using Kagi - and paying for it - for a year, to me the answer is a “yes”.
Making Kagi a paid search engine finally aligns the needs of the users with the
needs of the customers, because now these are the same people. I no longer see
search results because the advertisers want me to see them. The end result is a
service that is worth paying for. There are some caveats, which I will get to
in a moment.</p>
<p>Kagi offers several subscription plans. I am not going to comment on the
affordability, since that is going to be different for everyone depending on
income. I will warn about the free trial though. Kagi allows you to try a
hundred searches for free. This is how I started at first, but quickly noticed
that, since the number of searches was limited, I would tend to use DuckDuckGo
by default, and only use Kagi if DDG failed. That doesn’t really give the true
taste of Kagi’s usability. It wasn’t until I decided to try the paid plan for a
single month that I really saw the benefits of Kagi. I also have some
scepticism about Kagi’s Starter plan that, at the moment of this writing, offers
300 searches a month. Kagi quotes statistics from Google and DuckDuckGo, which
claim an average of 100 and 30 (sic!) monthly searches per user, respectively.
I find these numbers unbelievably low. Kagi offers search statistics, and I can
see there was not a single month when I would use less than 300 searches. I
typically perform 340 searches a month, though there have been months when that
number went up to nearly 600. And that is only when using Kagi on the desktop.
My wife, who uses Kagi on desktop and mobile, has an average of 200 searches
more per month<a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"><sup>3</sup></a>.</p>
<h2 id="features">Features</h2>
<p>Searching is obviously the most important thing in a search engine, but Kagi has
a few more features. Let’s have a brief look at some of them.</p>
<p>Firstly, Kagi offers lenses, which can be though of as a predefined set of
filters. For example, there’s an academic lens that will search for results on
web pages related to science and academia. There are a bunch of others, for
example usenet archives, fediverse forums, programming or recipes.</p>
<p>One kind of lens that deserves a special mention is the <a href="https://blog.kagi.com/small-web">Small
Web</a>. This is Kagi’s initiative to promote
personal websites and blogs, as they can be a great source of original opinions
and knowledge.</p>
<p>Kagi also works on adding LLM capabilities to the search experience. This is
one feature I am very sceptical about - I don’t share the hype around AI - and
the Kagi team definitely is well aware of the concerns surrounding AI and
ensures that user privacy is maintained, and no data generated by Kagi users is
used for training. As part of the standard payment plans, Kagi offers the Fast
Answer, which can be triggered by appending a question mark at the end of the
query. This will send the question to a LLM and provide an AI-generated answer,
together with references to sources from which the information was taken. This
feature works just like all the other large language models of today:
unreliably. Sometimes it gives good answers, and sometimes it fails, often in
subtle and non-obvious ways. For this reason, I approach this feature with
caution. Kagi also offers an AI
<a href="https://blog.kagi.com/announcing-assistant">Assistant</a> as part of the most
expensive Ultimate plan, but I have not tested it<a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4" role="doc-noteref"><sup>4</sup></a>.</p>
<p>There is also the Summarizer, embedded into the Kagi browser plugin (more on the
plugin in the next section), which can summarize the currently viewed web page.
I have only ever used the Summarizer to see if it works, and it seems to do the
job.</p>
<p>Kagi offers a lot of customization options. It is possible to customize the
layout of the search result page, either by choosing from predefined settings or
by providing a custom CSS for the results page. This, I have to say, is pretty
cool. Beyond that, one can create custom lenses and select which pre-defined
ones should be available. It is also possible to customize which widgets should
be available on the search results page.</p>
<p>Importantly, Kagi does not have search history, which I consider to be a good
privacy feature. To <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37561264">quote the founder of
Kagi</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Just to make it clear, Kagi does not link searches to an account already, to
begin with. Refer to our privacy policy. We simply do not need that data for
anything and it would be just a liability for us.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That being said, Kagi does offer the option to customize search results by
selecting which pages to consider more important and which ones to ignore.
There’s even a <a href="https://kagi.com/stats?stat=leaderboard">ranking of search stats and website
popularity</a>.</p>
<p>And finally, if any of the above features does not work as expected, there’s
<a href="https://kagifeedback.org/">Kagi Feedback</a> that allows to report bugs and
suggest features. What I find impressive is that the founder of Kagi himself
often responds to bug reports.</p>
<h2 id="cons-to-be-aware-of">Cons to be aware of</h2>
<p>As already stated, I am very pleased with Kagi and I think it offers better
search results than other search engines I have tried so far. However, not all
search result from Kagi are good. For example, Kagi will sometimes point to
those weird generic pages that have paragraphs of text seemingly on the subject,
but not really having any real information. (Not all of those pages are
AI-generated, so perhaps that’s why they are difficult to filter out?)
Sometimes Kagi will include scam sites in the results, and sometimes it will
just not show you the obviously correct results. A great example of this is
searching for “youtube downloader”. <code>yt-dlp</code> is the result that you most likely
want, but instead you get a bunch of SEO spam. But even with that happening
occasionally, I still think the quality of Kagi search results is above its
competitors. I have not yet been in a situation where DDG or Google would find
a search result that Kagi couldn’t find.</p>
<p>One big problem with Kagi is using it as the default search engine. This is
tricky for two reasons. Firstly, Kagi is a paid service that requires one to be
logged in, which presents an obvious problem when browsing in private mode.
Secondly, certain browsers and OSes either only allow a certain set of
predefined search engines or require a lot of effort to add a new search engine.
Kagi’s <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41164462">team struggles to get around those
limitations</a>, but from the
perspective of a user, the whole experience can be frustrating. I use Firefox
on desktop and in order to have Kagi work in private mode I had to install an
extension. However, on mobile, I was unable to use Kagi at all. In mobile
Firefox it should be possible to add a new search engine with a custom search
URL, and Kagi provides a session link with a login token to make this work. For
some reason, this does not work on my phone, although the same exact method
works without problems on my wife’s phone. And then many mobile browsers, for
example Vivaldi, won’t even allow you to add a custom search engine. As a
result, I still have to use DuckDuckGo on my Android.</p>
<p>Another minor issue with Kagi is that it is clearly tailored for Americans. For
example, a comma is not recognized as a decimal separator in certain contexts.
If I search Kagi for “2.5USD in PLN” it activates a widget that gives me an
immediate response, but if I replace the dot with a comma and search for “2,5USD
in PLN” the widget does not work. This is minor and things are improving - it
used to be the case that a comma was not recognized at all as a decimal
separator, so asking Kagi for things like “2,5 * 2” would return a range “{2,5}”
instead of “5”.</p>
<p>Any map related searches are also far from being perfect, to say the least.
Kagi at least recognizes that and provides easy links to Google Maps and Apple
Maps from their map search. Long story short, every time I need to find local
information on the map, I revert to Google.</p>
<p>Lastly, image search returns essentially the same results as all the other
search engines, so there is really no difference here.</p>
<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>For me, Kagi is one of the biggest discoveries of the past few years, and <strong>I
cannot afford not to use Kagi.</strong> It might not be perfect, but it has certainly
improved my web searching experience. Importantly, it has also given me hope
for a better web, one where the user’s needs are at the centre. I am curious to
see where the project goes, and in particular <a href="https://blog.kagi.com/dawn-new-era-search">how it aims to challenge Google’s
search monopoly</a>.</p>
<section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Quote comes from “The Anatomy of a Large-Scale Hypertextual Web Search
Engine” paper, from Appendix A titled “Advertising and Mixed Motives”.
Text of the paper available
<a href="http://infolab.stanford.edu/~backrub/google.html">here</a>.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>While writing this post, I also decided to test Bing. Not only the
results are garbage, but the results page is absolutely cluttered with
widgets and whatnot.<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>My wife and I did some investigation of this, since the number of extra
searches felt surprisingly high. Turns out that the number is
artificially bumped, because switching to a tab that wasn’t active for a
while in a mobile browser will cause the page in that tab to be reloaded.
If you switch to a tab that contains Kagi search result, this reload will
trigger a new search of the previously searched term.<a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Speaking of Kagi Assistant, I also think Kagi might have created <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Lznc7p43nos">one of
the worst commercials ever</a>,
which is a real shame.<a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>27/09/2024</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2024-09-27-goodbye-google-switching-from-google-search-to-kagi.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Four years of using a custom-built small form factor desktop PC</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 27/08/2024
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc">Four years of using a custom-built small form factor desktop PC</h1>
<p>For the past four years, I have been using a desktop PC I have custom-built to
my own needs. One of its key features is that it combines high-end computing
power with a small form factor (SFF). My motivation to write this post came
from a recent online discussion I participated in, where someone not familiar
with SFF PCs tried to convince me (and others) that SFF PCs are bound to
overheat. As a long-time user of an SFF PC, I can safely say this is not true
and it such <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fear,_uncertainty,_and_doubt">FUD</a>
needs to be dismissed. I also want to share my experiences of building a small
form factor desktop PC, so that those of you interested in doing an SFF build
know where the challenges lie.</p>
<h2 id="a-bit-of-personal-history">A bit of personal history</h2>
<p>The last time I built a desktop PC was back in 2006. It was an Athlon 64-based
platform. A distinguishing feature of my build was the case. I went for a
Chieftec Dragon mid-tower, made of thick aluminium and weighing 8kg. I thought
of it as a once-in-a-lifetime investment, just like a Parker pen. I was not
entirely wrong. The case still serves for my mum’s PC, though the internals
have long been replaced.</p>
<p>In 2011, I rented a small studio flat and started living on my own. I no longer
had the space for a large desktop PC and have switched to using a laptop.
Compared to a desktop, usability was quite bad, but I appreciated the mobility.</p>
<p>In the second half of 2019 I was thinking of getting a new computer. The
release of Cyberpunk 2077 was approaching fast, and I was planning to get a
proper gaming PC just in time for the premiere. (It would also be the first
time in my life to even have a gaming PC.) I was also quite tired of having to
work on laptops - the ergonomics were proving to be very bad for my health. As
a quick stop-gap solution, towards the end of 2019, I bought an external
keyboard and a 23" LCD and used both with my laptop. Having worked with
them for a couple of days, it was settled: I am going back to having a proper
desktop PC. No more struggling with laptop ergonomics.</p>
<p>That was late 2019. In early 2020, COVID happened. Cyberpunk 2077 was delayed
a couple of months, initially to September. However, seeing how the pandemic
wreaks havoc in the electronic supply chains, in March I decided to proceed with
the plan of building a desktop PC. As you’ll see in a moment, it was already a
bit too late.</p>
<h2 id="deciding-on-a-small-form-factor-build">Deciding on a small form factor build</h2>
<p>When the <em>“small form factor”</em> term comes around, some of you might think of one
of the mini computers, such as the Intel NUC or HP Elite. That wouldn’t be
entirely wrong - these count as SFF desktops - but what I mean by SFF are small
desktop cases produced for PC enthusiasts. I was sold on the idea of a small
form factor PC by a friend of mine, who built his desktop in a <a href="https://www.dan-cases.com/dana4.php">Dan
A4-SFX</a>. It is one of the best SFF cases
on the market with dimensions of 20cm x 12cm x 32cm and just 7.2L of volume.
With such a small size, my friend just treats his computer as a portable PC for
game jams.</p>
<p>Don’t be fooled by the small dimensions. As you’ll see, these PCs can fit the
most powerful CPUs and GPUs. In fact, the best SFF cases are produced in small
numbers for enthusiasts who want to get the best possible performance, while
keeping their PC small.</p>
<p>From the beginning, <strong>I liked the idea of having a PC that’s actually small
enough to fit on my desk</strong>. I still had the memory of that huge Chieftec Dragon
case and how I struggled to fit it under the table. I’ve seen my friend’s PC in
action and envied how small it was. And so I decided to go with an SFF build.</p>
<p>I was planning on building a PC that is suitable for both gaming and work. For
gaming, I wanted an RTX card - these came to the market just a few months prior.
For work, I wanted a CPU with as many cores as possible. My major use case is
program compilation, and that’s when many cores definitely pay off.</p>
<h2 id="selecting-the-components">Selecting the components</h2>
<p>Having figured out my use cases and requirements, I was in for a lot of
research. One thing I quickly learned is that building a small form factor PC
is a bit like solving a puzzle. It is certainly an art of compromises, as one
cannot just put any components into the case.</p>
<p>The first choice to make was crucial: AMD or Intel? In the past, I had
experiences with both. While I still fondly remember my Xeon-based laptop, I
try not to take any sympathies with any of the companies and just pick the best
product. In 2020, it was certainly AMD, which made a spectacular comeback after
years of falling behind Intel. I decided to go for a Ryzen 9 3900X, a
12-core/24-thread CPU whose multiple cores would allow me to speed up my most
common use case - code compilation. Intel had practically nothing comparable to
offer, and getting an AMD was an obvious choice.</p>
<p>Once the platform was decided, it was time for the motherboard. The majority of
small form factor cases will only fit mini-ITX motherboards, which are 17cm by
17cm. These will have just one PCIe expansion slot and one pair of RAM
slots. Luckily, these are the only compromises one needs to make. Other than
that, mini-ITX boards can be as performant and feature-rich as their full-sized
ATX counterparts. I was planning to get a motherboard based on either B450 or
X470 chipset, but I was out of luck as all such motherboards have sold out by
April 2020, and it didn’t seem like they are coming back in stock anytime soon.
As an act of desperation, I had to get a <a href="https://rog.asus.com/motherboards/rog-crosshair/rog-crosshair-viii-impact-model">ROG Crosshair VIII
Impact</a>.
It is a high-end motherboard based on the X570 chipset, designed with
overlocking in mind. Unfortunately, for this reason it is quite expensive,
about a double of what I had originally intended to pay for a motherboard. As a
bonus problem, Crosshair VIII Impact has a mini-DTX format instead of mini-ITX.
This means an additional 3 centimetres in length, making it 20x17cm instead of
17x17cm, and impossible to fit in most SFF cases.</p>
<p>Luckily for me, by that time I have already decided on the <a href="https://ncased.com/products/m1-classic">NCase
M1</a>. With dimensions of 33cm x 16cm x
24cm and a total volume o 12.7 litres, it is larger than many SFF cases. It
also can fit a mini-DTX board. I remember my wife having serious doubts about
the M1 due to its price - it had to be imported from Taiwan, adding even further
to the costs - but once she saw how well the M1 is made and how modular it is,
she agreed it was absolutely worth the money.</p>
<p>Next, the power supply unit (PSU). SFF PCs typically use PSUs in the SFX
format, a smaller variant of the typical ATX format. Choosing a power supply
was a no-brainer - Corsair offers the best SFX power supplies on the market.
One really nice feature they have is modularity: cables that are not needed can
be disconnected from the power supply, instead of dangling inside the case.
Unfortunately, pandemic once again proved to be a pain. I was planning to get a
750W PSU, but the only one I could source was a 600W one. Luckily, 600 Watt was
enough for my build.</p>
<p>Finally, the graphics card. When it comes to building an SFF computer, <strong>GPU
compatibility is something that needs to be taken into account</strong>. Graphics
cards have got quite large these days, often taking as much as three expansion
slots and having three fans on the radiator. Many of the largest cards will not
fit into an SFF computer<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a>. I had to take those limitations into account and
ultimately decided on the EVGA GeForce RTX 2070 Super Black Gaming<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a>, a 2-fan
2-slot card that fits perfectly in the M1. Interestingly, I was able to get the
GPU just fine - major shortages didn’t happen until the second half of 2020.</p>
<p>Aside from that, I decided on 16GB of RAM memory (Corsair Vengence LPX) and
Seagate FireCuda 510 2TB NVMe drive.</p>
<h2 id="cooling">Cooling</h2>
<p>Figuring out the cooling is a whole separate subject. <strong>This is one thing that
needs to be done right with an SFF build.</strong></p>
<p>SFF cases tend to have quite strict limitations on CPU cooler height, though the
M1 is generous in that regard. After considering my options I decided on the
<a href="https://noctua.at/en/nh-u9s">Noctua NH-U9S</a> radiator with two 92mm
<a href="https://noctua.at/en/nf-a9-pwm">NF-A9</a> fans working as the exhaust. I also
mounted a 120mm intake fan on the side bracket. The plan was to have the side
fan pull air into the case, and the CPU fans exhaust it at the back. This was
the starting point, but it needs a few words of comment.</p>
<p>Firstly, having two fans on the cooler proved to be inconvenient when removing
the cooler from the CPU. I didn’t think this would be a problem since I wasn’t
planning to take off the cooler once the PC was assembled. However, I ended up
assembing and disassembling the computer several times. In the end I decided to
remove the rear fan from the CPU cooler and attach it to a dedicated place at
the back of the case. Cooling works essentially the same, but disassembling the
CPU cooler is now a lot easier.</p>
<p>Secondly, I’ve run into unexpected problems with the GPU. The graphics card I
picked had a semi-passive cooling, meaning the fans only turn on once the
temperature reaches 55C. This looks like a great idea on paper, but its
execution is flawed. It turns out that during regular desktop work card’s
temperature oscilates around the 55C mark, resulting in fans constantly turning
on and off. I probably wouldn’t have noticed if it wasn’t for a loud, audiable
click every time the fans start or stop, i.e. every 10 seconds. Sadly, the card
BIOS isn’t smart enough to spot such situations and just keep the fans on. A
solution was to mount extra fans underneath the card. M1 allows to mount two
fans at the bottom of the case, which I did. Of course, any extra fans under
the GPU defeat the purpose of passive cooling on the card.</p>
<p>Now, let’s talk about the fans. Last time I assembled a PC back in 2006 the
go-to brand when one wanted the best fans was Akasa. Indeed, they were great.
Quiet and extremely durable - the ones I got in 2006 still work without any
audiable buzz. Apparently, things have changed since then and in 2020 the brand
everyone recommends is Noctua. Because of that universal apprisal I decided to
go with Noctua fans. Unfortunatelly, despite good opinions, Noctua fans turned
out to be a major disappointment. I expect three qualities from a fan: it needs
to be effective, quiet, and durable. Noctua manages with the first and third
requirement, but not with the second one. I would expect that the only noise
comming from a fan is the hum of the air going through it. However, most of the
Noctua fans I bought emit a buzz and sometimes also vibrations (despite rubber
anti-vibration pads).</p>
<p>I initially started with five fans installed inside the case - two on the CPU,
two under the GPU, one on the side. Most of them would be faulty and buzz. I
went through several returns, RMAs, and experiments with different models
(Chromax, Redux). I had around a total of 10-12 Noctua fans go through my hands
before I finally found ones that weren’t buzzing. I also gave up on the idea of
two fans under the GPU. I couldn’t find the fifth fan that didn’t buzz and it
turned out that a single fan is enought to keep the GPU at 40C during standard
desktop work.</p>
<p>I admit that the four fans I settled on have been working fine for the past four
years without any problems, but the fact that majority of the fans I bought were
deffective is simply unacceptable. With such experience I can safely say that
<strong>Noctua fans are utter garbage and I don’t recommend them to anyone</strong>. I won’t
even mention the questionable colour choice Noctua has made with their fans -
luckily, there’s the Noctua Chromax line, which offers black fans.</p>
<p>Lastly, some people might want to consider liquid cooling. The NCase M1 is
designed for that, as are most SFF cases. The side bracket in the M1 allows to
mount a radiator with two 120mm fans, while at the back are two holes for those
wanting a custom liquid cooling loop connected to an external reservoir. The
reason why I didn’t go for water cooling was the uncertainty surrounding the
Linux support of water coolers. Back in 2020 there was no official Linux
software to control the water pumps. (Have things changed in 2024? Somehow, I
doubt it.) I didn’t want to end up with cooling that doesn’t work as intended
and decided to stick to the traditional air cooling.</p>
<h2 id="the-build">The build</h2>
<p>Here are some photos from the build process:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/component_test.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/component_test_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Testing the components before installing them inside the case.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/components_in_case.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/components_in_case_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Putting components inside the case.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/first_build_assembled.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/first_build_assembled_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Side bracket with the intake cooling fan installed. Dust filters
and panels still missing. Note the power cable mess lying on the GPU and two
fans below the card.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/top_view.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/top_view_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Top view. Note the two fans attached to the CPU cooler.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<h2 id="temperatures">Temperatures</h2>
<p>The first thing I did after finishing the build was running the benchmarks, to
stress-test both the CPU (using <a href="https://www.mersenne.org/">Prime95</a>) and the
GPU (using <a href="https://geeks3d.com/furmark/">Furmark</a>). With CPU, I was able to
heat it up to about 90C, while benchmarking GPU yielded a 76C temperature.
However, these results differ from temperatures obtained during daily usage.</p>
<p>The CPU’s idle temperature was originally around 44-45C, though over the years
it would slightly rise to around 48-49C. I presume this is due to thermal paste
deterioration. During daily usage, I found it extremely difficult to heat the
CPU past the 70C mark, even if compiling on all cores for a longer period of
time. Note that I have disabled Core Performance Boost in the BIOS. Core
Performance Boost is like a factory CPU overlock. Disabling it results in
lowering the CPU voltage from 1.4V to 1.0V and thus lowering the idle
temperatures noticeably. This comes at a marginal loss of computing power,
which is something I am willing to accept for a noticeable reduction in power
consumption, thermals, and fan noise.</p>
<p>The GPU’s idle temperature with one fan underneath it typically sits at around
40C, with a power draw of about 20 Watts. These numbers are for Linux.
Interestingly, on Windows the GPU idle temperatures are closer to the 55C mark,
resulting in fans repeatedly going on and off. When playing games, the highest
temperature I got was 80C in Metro: Exodus. This is higher than in the
benchmarks, suggesting that Furmark might not be able to fully saturate the
card.</p>
<h2 id="upgrades">Upgrades</h2>
<p>One thing I always had at the back of my head when building a PC are the upgrade
options. From experience, I know it is quite difficult to predict the future
upgradability of the assembled configuration. That being said, for this
particular build things have gone well since I already upgraded the RAM, the CPU
and the GPU.</p>
<p>In early 2022, I upgraded the original 16GB of RAM to 32GB. This was motivated
by requirements of <a href="https://nixos.org/">Nix</a> and is something I intend to write
about on the blog. The tricky bit with this upgrade is that the DDR4 memory
these days comes in pairs of modules. However, small motherboards used in SFF
computers have only two RAM slots. As a result, it is not possible to simply
add more memory. Therefore, when upgrading RAM, I had to remove and replace
existing memory, which left me with a pair of unneeded memory modules that I had
to sell.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, I decided to upgrade both the CPU and the GPU. I swapped the
3900X with a Ryzen 9 5950X, which is a 16-core/32-thread CPU. The 5950X has the
same TDP (thermal design power = amount of emitted heat) as the old 3900X, which
means no modification to the existing cooling was needed. After the upgrade, I
noticed a decrease in CPU temperatures, but I don’t know whether this is due to
better thermal performance of the new CPU or just because of new thermal paste.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/cpu_replacement.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/cpu_replacement_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Replacing the CPU.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As for the GPU, I went for <a href="https://www.inno3d.com/product/inno3d-geforce-rtx-4070-super-twin-x2">Inno3D GeForce RTX 4070 Super Twin
X2</a>. I
built my PC in the first half of 2020, and in September of that year, nVidia
released the RTX 30xx series. The 30xx cards were noticeably larger and would
no longer fit the M1. I was concerned that I won’t be able to upgrade the GPU
without replacing the case, but luckily with the RTX 40xx series, nVidia has
done a great job at minimizing the cards. The new RTX 4070 Super is smaller and
draws roughly the same amount of power, while being several times more powerful
than the 2070 Super - <strong>I am truly impressed with what nVidia have achieved
here</strong>. At the same time, the 4070 Supers are quite affordable, certainly a lot
cheaper than what I paid for the 2070 Super in 2020. The only real downside is
the new GPU power connector, the infamous 12VHPWR, which is a major pain. It
lacks flexibility and getting the side panel to close after installing the new
card was a challenge.</p>
<p>I have also run into an unexpected compatibility issue between the new card and
the motherboard. The 4070 Super has a backplate and the card would not fit into
the PCIe slot due to collision with the cooling block at the back of the
motherboard. The solution was to remove one of the screws holding the backplate
- this resulted in an extra 0.5mm of space, which was enough to fit the new card.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/gpu_size_comparison.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/gpu_size_comparison_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Size comparison between RTX 4070 Super (top) and RTX 2070 Super
(bottom). Notice the small PCB on the 4070 (top right).
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/side_view.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/side_view_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
After 4 years of usage. Note there is just one fan under the GPU
and the power cables have been properly organized. The side bracket is covered
with a dust filter.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/side_view_no_bracket.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/side_view_no_bracket_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Side bracket removed. The rear fan has been moved from the CPU
cooler to the back of the case.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/gpu_replaced.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/gpu_replaced_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
4070 Super installed. The new 12VHPWR power connector is a major
pain: side panel barely fits, and cable management is again a bit of a mess.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/tight_gpu_fit.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc/tight_gpu_fit_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
There’s literally no space between the backplate of the 4070 Super
and the motherboard’s cooling block. Removing a screw was necessary to make the
card fit.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<h2 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h2>
<p>After 4 years of using an SFF PC, I couldn’t be more happy with it. With a
16C/32T CPU and 32GB of RAM, it has all the computing power I need for work,
while a powerful GPU makes it also a high-end gaming PC. <strong>I never had any
problems with the temperatures, which are at a level comparable with a standard
PC. The single most important part of this success is the NCase M1.</strong> It is
small enough not to be a problem when standing on the desk. At the same time,
it has all the space needed to fit the components and provide them with proper
cooling. I am also very happy about the upgradability of the whole build.</p>
<p>This was my first SFF build, and it took a lot of research. I started thinking
about the new PC sometime in March 2020, and the build was ultimately finished
in July. Most of that time was spent waiting for a 750W power supply that never
arrived. Another 3 weeks went wasted because of the motherboard failure. The
one I originally got, died after a week. I had to disassemble the whole
computer, RMA the motherboard, wait for a replacement, and assemble everything
again.</p>
<p>Building a PC during the pandemic was also quite a challenge. I ended up
getting parts that I didn’t exactly want, but in the end I am not complaining.
The Crosshair VIII Impact motherboard proved to be a decent platform for future
upgrades, while the 600W power supply is, quite surprisingly, enough to power
both the new CPU and the new GPU.</p>
<p>The whole process of building my own SFF PC was greatly aided by the
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/@OptimumTech">OptimumTech channel on YouTube</a>. This is
a treasure trove of knowledge and I highly recommend you check it out if you
decide to make your own SFF build. Note that here I have only focused on my own
experiences and haven’t talked about SFF builds in general. In particular, I
haven’t even mentioned sandwich layouts, i.e. mounting the GPU parallel to the
motherboard using a riser cable, instead of inserting the GPU into a PCIe slot.
So, if you want to learn about that, OptimumTech’s channel is the place to go.</p>
<p>This post has got a lot longer than I initially intended. I plan to follow it
up with two more posts. One will be about the AMD’s AM4 platform and its
stability issues, while the other about being an early RTX adopter.</p>
<section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>SFF cases have progressed noticeably since 2020 and are much better at
space management. For example, the successor of my M1 case, <a href="https://ncased.com/collections/m-series/products/m2-round">NCase
M2</a>, fits the
majority of GPUs on the market. Still, there are some large cards that it
will not fit.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Sadly, in September 2022 <a href="https://www.tomshardware.com/news/evga-abandons-the-gpu-market-reportedly-citing-conflicts-with-nvidia">EVGA decided to withdraw from the GPU
market</a>,
the supposed reason being difficult partnership with nVidia.<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>27/08/2024</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2024-08-27-four-years-of-using-a-custom-built-small-form-factor-desktop-pc.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Fremen Zone&#58; Creating a Website Using Only HTML and CSS</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2024-08-21-fremen-zone-creating-a-website-using-only-html-and-css.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 21/08/2024
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="fremen-zone-creating-a-website-using-only-html-and-css">Fremen Zone: Creating a Website Using Only HTML and CSS</h1>
<p>A year ago in July I wrote <a href="2023-07-12-all-the-things-ive-ever-done-wrong-with-my-websites.html">a post about all the websites that I have run in my
life</a>. An
important part of that list was Fremen Zone, a fansite dedicated to Frank
Herbert’s “Dune”. It was my first website ever, which I created back in high
school and have <a href="https://www.fremenzone.pl/legacy/index.htm">restored last year from backups on my hard
drive</a>. I ended the post with an
idea of creating a new version of Fremen Zone:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Restoring the Fremen Zone back to life sparked a new desire in me. While I
said I have no intention of updating it, I feel like re-doing the whole site
from scratch. (…) And so I am slowly gathering material for a new Dune
fanpage. All the lessons above have taught me to avoid complexity and stay as
close to the basics as possible. And so my plan is to create a new website
based on pure HTML and CSS.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Since late June 2023 I have been hard at work to create a new version of Fremen
Zone. The website went live on February 1st 2024 and is available at
<a href="https://www.fremenzone.pl" class="uri">https://www.fremenzone.pl</a>. In this post I want to talk about the technical
aspects of the new Fremen Zone page, in particular putting emphasis on
simplicity and developing a dedicated static page generator.</p>
<p>Now, one tiny detail before we move on. If you clicked on the link below, you
already noticed that Fremen Zone is in Polish, not English. Google Translate
does a decent job at translating it to English, but make sure to fold the
translation bar. Otherwise it covers the top navigation bar.</p>
<h2 id="keeping-things-simple">Keeping things simple</h2>
<p>The primary principle driving the technical design of the new page was to keep
technical solutions as simple as possible. I didn’t want to rely on any
existing frameworks, content management systems, or anything of that sort.
Instead, I wanted to create a website that uses only HTML5 and CSS, with no
JavaScript. The goal was to make a page that is static, small (=quick to load),
fast and responsive, without bloat, and also easy to deploy or move to a
different hosting.</p>
<p>The first step was layout design. The old Fremen Zone used frames, which nobody
really relies on today. For the new version, I decided to go with a navigation
menu placed at the top of the page. This layout looks clean and minimalistic,
which is one of the things I wanted to achieve with the new website.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-08-21-fremen-zone-creating-a-website-using-only-html-and-css/navbar.png"><img src="/images/posts/2024-08-21-fremen-zone-creating-a-website-using-only-html-and-css/navbar_thumbnail.png" /></a>
<figcaption>
The navigation bar highlights the current section. Below the navbar is a section logo.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I haven’t done any front-end programming since my original work on Fremen Zone
nearly quarter a century ago, so not only have I forgotten everything I learned
about HTML and CSS back then, but also both standards have evolved over time.
And so I was learning HTML5 and CSS from scratch as I worked on the new page
design. An important change made to HTML since its early days is the
introduction of tags that carry important semantic meaning. And so the
navigation bar is enclosed in <code>&lt;nav&gt;&lt;/nav&gt;</code> tags, sub-page headers use
<code>&lt;header&gt;&lt;/header&gt;</code> tag, and so on – whenever semantic tags were available I
made sure to use them, though I didn’t get everything right on first attempt.
More on that in a moment.</p>
<h2 id="browser-compatibility">Browser compatibility</h2>
<p>One of my top technical priorities was browser compatibility. I wanted to make
sure that the website will work as intended, no matter the browser. This is
something I have put a lot of attention to when designing the original Fremen
Zone two decades ago. The difference is that back then I tested the page with
Internet Explorer and Netscape Navigator, while now the tested browsers included
Firefox (that’s my default browser), Chromium (I avoid Chrome like a plague, but
acknowledge the fact that most people use it), <a href="https://www.palemoon.org/">Pale
Moon</a>
(pre-<a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/en/mozilla/introducing-firefox-quantum/">Quantum</a>
fork of Firefox), <a href="http://links.twibright.com/">links</a> and
<a href="https://lynx.invisible-island.net/">lynx</a> (terminal-based text-only web
browsers), <a href="https://dillo-browser.github.io/">Dillo</a> (an extremely minimalistic
web browser), and <a href="https://www.torproject.org/">Tor</a> (privacy-focused web
browser based on Firefox). Despite the multitude of modern browsers, the task
was generally easier than 25 years ago.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-08-21-fremen-zone-creating-a-website-using-only-html-and-css/firefox.png"><img src="/images/posts/2024-08-21-fremen-zone-creating-a-website-using-only-html-and-css/firefox_thumbnail.png" /></a>
<figcaption>
Intended page rendering in Firefox.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The new version of Fremen Zone renders as intended in Firefox, Chromium and Pale
Moon. However, the more obscure browsers don’t always render the page as
intended. For example, Dillo does not correctly handle CSS margins and width
attributes, resulting, among others, in misaligned section logo images and
incorrect text width:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-08-21-fremen-zone-creating-a-website-using-only-html-and-css/dillo.png"><img src="/images/posts/2024-08-21-fremen-zone-creating-a-website-using-only-html-and-css/dillo_thumbnail.png" /></a>
<figcaption>
Dillo does not handle text flow as intended. As a bonus, the
background of the main page logo has the wrong colour.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Tor on the other hand, as part of its security measures, blocks web fonts. This
results in incorrect rendering of the RSS icon on the right of the navigation
bar (see <a href="#polishing-the-details">Polishing the details</a> section below for more
details on web fonts).</p>
<p>It was a fun exercise to get the page to look readable in text-based web
browsers. These browsers are obviously quite limited at what they can do, but
one thing they forced me to get right was correct semantic usage of HTML tags.
For example, I first started out with using stylized <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> tags for the
headers and sub-headers on the page. This looked as intended in graphical
browsers, but in text-based ones the headers rendered as a one-line paragraphs
of text and were indistinguishable from normal paragraphs. The solution was to
switch to dedicated header tags, <code>&lt;h1&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;h2&gt;</code>. In graphical browsers this
makes no difference since the styling is handled with CSS. However, text-based
browsers now interpret headers correctly and make them stand out from the rest
of the text.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-08-21-fremen-zone-creating-a-website-using-only-html-and-css/lynx.png"><img src="/images/posts/2024-08-21-fremen-zone-creating-a-website-using-only-html-and-css/lynx_thumbnail.png" /></a>
<figcaption>
Fremen Zone rendering in Lynx. Note the repeated navbar.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I also wanted Fremen Zone to display correctly on mobile devices. In principle,
I don’t really care much about smartphones - I consider them a horrible way of
interacting with the Internet and rarely use mine to browse the web. But at the
same time, I thought of this as in interesting technical challenge and a
learning opportunity.</p>
<p>The biggest problem to overcome with rendering Fremen Zone on mobile was the
navigation bar. Firstly, the navbar is structured differently on desktop and on
mobile, forcing two copies of it to be defined in the source code. At any given
time, only one of those copies is visible, which is controlled by the <code>@media</code>
at-rules in CSS. Text-based browsers don’t handle <code>@media</code> at-rules as intended
and display both copies of the menu at the same time. Hence, the repeated
navbar in the screenshot above.</p>
<p>The mobile version of the navigation bar, instead of a list of available page
sections, contains only a “hamburger menu” icon. The proper menu becomes
visible once the icon is clicked. Sadly, getting this behaviour to work
requires a short JavaScript snippet attached via the <code>&lt;a&gt;</code> tag’s <code>onclick</code>
property. It isn’t a long script, just a few lines of code to add or remove a
CSS class that switches menu visibility, but it means that my goal of creating a
website that does not use JavaScript at all was not possible to achieve. Not
without giving up on mobile responsiveness, at least. I spent hours
experimenting with different approaches, hoping I can get things to work with
just CSS, but to no avail. I accepted that I need these few lines of JavaScript
and moved on.</p>
<p>Finally, there was the question of compatibility with various mobile browsers.
Luckily, things went much smoother than on desktop. Essentially all browsers I
tested - Firefox, DuckDuckGo, Vivaldi, Opera Mini, Edge - rendered the page as
intended.</p>
<h2 id="writing-a-custom-website-generator">Writing a custom website generator</h2>
<p>I spent approximately two weeks prototyping the layout. Once the initial design
was in place I began preliminary work on the contents. After creating several
subpages it quickly became apparent that pages contain lots of repetition, in
particular in the <code>&lt;head&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;navbar&gt;</code> tags. Surely, there were minor
differences - each page had a different <code>&lt;title&gt;</code> and each subpage’s navbar
highlighted a different current section - but the overall structure of each page
was identical. It was clear at this point that this repetition must be
eliminated. And so the next step was to write a custom static website
generator.</p>
<p>I decided to put each logical fragment of the page into a separate template
file. For example, template for the page’s HTML header contains:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1"><pre class="sourceCode html"><code class="sourceCode html"><span id="cb1-1"><a href="#cb1-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="dt">&lt;</span><span class="kw">head</span><span class="dt">&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-2"><a href="#cb1-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>  <span class="dt">&lt;</span><span class="kw">meta</span><span class="ot"> charset</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;utf-8&quot;</span><span class="dt">&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-3"><a href="#cb1-3" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>  <span class="dt">&lt;</span><span class="kw">meta</span><span class="ot"> name</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;viewport&quot;</span><span class="ot"> content</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0&quot;</span><span class="dt">&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-4"><a href="#cb1-4" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>  <span class="dt">&lt;</span><span class="kw">meta</span><span class="ot"> name</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;author&quot;</span><span class="ot"> content</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;Jan Stolarek&quot;</span><span class="dt">&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-5"><a href="#cb1-5" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>  <span class="dt">&lt;</span><span class="kw">link</span><span class="ot"> rel</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;preload&quot;</span><span class="ot"> as</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;font&quot;</span><span class="ot"> type</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;font/woff2&quot;</span><span class="ot"> href</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;RELPATH/fonts/fa-solid-900.woff2&quot;</span><span class="ot"> crossorigin</span><span class="dt">&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-6"><a href="#cb1-6" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>  <span class="dt">&lt;</span><span class="kw">link</span><span class="ot"> rel</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;preload&quot;</span><span class="ot"> as</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;style&quot;</span><span class="ot"> type</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;text/css&quot;</span><span class="ot"> href</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;RELPATH/styl.css&quot;</span><span class="dt">&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-7"><a href="#cb1-7" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>  <span class="dt">&lt;</span><span class="kw">link</span><span class="ot"> rel</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;preload&quot;</span><span class="ot"> as</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;image&quot;</span><span class="ot"> type</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;image/png&quot;</span><span class="ot"> href</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;RELPATH/img/SECTION.png&quot;</span><span class="dt">&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-8"><a href="#cb1-8" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>  <span class="dt">&lt;</span><span class="kw">link</span><span class="ot"> rel</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;stylesheet&quot;</span><span class="ot"> type</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;text/css&quot;</span><span class="ot"> href</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;RELPATH/styl.css&quot;</span><span class="dt">&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-9"><a href="#cb1-9" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>  <span class="dt">&lt;</span><span class="kw">link</span><span class="ot"> rel</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;icon&quot;</span><span class="ot"> type</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;image/x-icon&quot;</span><span class="ot"> href</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;RELPATH/favicon.png&quot;</span><span class="dt">&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-10"><a href="#cb1-10" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>  <span class="dt">&lt;</span><span class="kw">link</span><span class="ot"> rel</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;license&quot;</span><span class="ot"> href</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;RELPATH/LICENCJA.md&quot;</span><span class="dt">&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-11"><a href="#cb1-11" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>  <span class="dt">&lt;</span><span class="kw">title</span><span class="dt">&gt;</span>PAGETITLE<span class="dt">&lt;/</span><span class="kw">title</span><span class="dt">&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-12"><a href="#cb1-12" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="dt">&lt;/</span><span class="kw">head</span><span class="dt">&gt;</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>Putting all those repeating fragments into their own template files allowed me
to reduce each page to just its proper contents enclosed inside a <code>&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</code>
block. Everything else - <code>&lt;head&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;navbar&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;header&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;footer&gt;</code>, etc. -
is stored in template files. This way all the repetition in HTML sources is
gone and changing, say, page’s <code>&lt;head&gt;</code> section requires modifying only the
respective template file.</p>
<p>I then wrote a bash script to assemble full HTML pages from templates and the
proper source files. At the heart of the script are the following lines:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb2"><pre class="sourceCode bash"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb2-1"><a href="#cb2-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="bu">echo</span> <span class="st">&quot;&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;&quot;</span>        <span class="op">&gt;</span>  <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-2"><a href="#cb2-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="bu">echo</span> <span class="st">&quot;&quot;</span>                       <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-3"><a href="#cb2-3" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="bu">echo</span> <span class="st">&quot;&lt;html lang=</span><span class="dt">\&quot;</span><span class="st">pl</span><span class="dt">\&quot;</span><span class="st">&gt;&quot;</span>     <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-4"><a href="#cb2-4" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="fu">cat</span> <span class="va">$TEMPLATEDIR</span>/head.html    <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-5"><a href="#cb2-5" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="bu">echo</span> <span class="st">&quot;&quot;</span>                       <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-6"><a href="#cb2-6" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="bu">echo</span> <span class="st">&quot;&lt;body&gt;&quot;</span>                 <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-7"><a href="#cb2-7" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="bu">echo</span> <span class="st">&quot;&quot;</span>                       <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-8"><a href="#cb2-8" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="fu">cat</span> <span class="va">$TEMPLATEDIR</span>/scripts.html <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-9"><a href="#cb2-9" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="bu">echo</span> <span class="st">&quot;&quot;</span>                       <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-10"><a href="#cb2-10" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="fu">cat</span> <span class="va">$TEMPLATEDIR</span>/navbar.html  <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-11"><a href="#cb2-11" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="bu">echo</span> <span class="st">&quot;&quot;</span>                       <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-12"><a href="#cb2-12" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="fu">cat</span> <span class="va">$TEMPLATEDIR</span>/header.html  <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-13"><a href="#cb2-13" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="bu">echo</span> <span class="st">&quot;&quot;</span>                       <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-14"><a href="#cb2-14" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="bu">echo</span> <span class="st">&quot;&lt;main&gt;&quot;</span>                 <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-15"><a href="#cb2-15" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="bu">echo</span> <span class="st">&quot;&quot;</span>                       <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-16"><a href="#cb2-16" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="fu">cat</span> <span class="va">$SRCDIR</span>/<span class="va">$FILEPATH</span>         <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-17"><a href="#cb2-17" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="bu">echo</span> <span class="st">&quot;&quot;</span>                       <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-18"><a href="#cb2-18" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="bu">echo</span> <span class="st">&quot;&lt;/main&gt;&quot;</span>                <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-19"><a href="#cb2-19" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="bu">echo</span> <span class="st">&quot;&quot;</span>                       <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-20"><a href="#cb2-20" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="fu">cat</span> <span class="va">$TEMPLATEDIR</span>/footer.html  <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-21"><a href="#cb2-21" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="bu">echo</span> <span class="st">&quot;&quot;</span>                       <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-22"><a href="#cb2-22" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="bu">echo</span> <span class="st">&quot;&lt;/body&gt;&quot;</span>                <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span>
<span id="cb2-23"><a href="#cb2-23" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="bu">echo</span> <span class="st">&quot;&lt;/html&gt;&quot;</span>                <span class="op">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>There are some bash variables in here, but their names should be
self-descriptive.</p>
<p>You might be wondering about the <code>RELPATH</code>, <code>SECTION</code>, and <code>PAGETITLE</code> words
used in the example template file above. These are reserved words that are
replaced with page-specific values using <code>sed</code>. This allows not only to have
page-specific titles and section logos, but also calculate relative paths:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb3"><pre class="sourceCode bash"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb3-1"><a href="#cb3-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="co"># Insert relative paths</span></span>
<span id="cb3-2"><a href="#cb3-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="cf">if</span> <span class="bu">[</span> <span class="st">&quot;</span><span class="va">$FILEDIR</span><span class="st">&quot;</span> <span class="ot">=</span> <span class="st">&quot;.&quot;</span> <span class="bu">]</span><span class="kw">;</span> <span class="cf">then</span></span>
<span id="cb3-3"><a href="#cb3-3" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>    <span class="va">RELPATH</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;.&quot;</span></span>
<span id="cb3-4"><a href="#cb3-4" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="cf">else</span></span>
<span id="cb3-5"><a href="#cb3-5" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>    <span class="va">SLASHES</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;</span><span class="va">${FILEDIR</span><span class="op">//</span><span class="ss">[^</span><span class="dt">\/</span><span class="ss">]</span><span class="va">}</span><span class="st">&quot;</span></span>
<span id="cb3-6"><a href="#cb3-6" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>    <span class="va">DIRDEPTH</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;</span><span class="va">${</span><span class="op">#</span><span class="va">SLASHES}</span><span class="st">&quot;</span></span>
<span id="cb3-7"><a href="#cb3-7" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>    <span class="va">RELPATH</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;..&quot;</span></span>
<span id="cb3-8"><a href="#cb3-8" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>    <span class="cf">for</span> i <span class="kw">in</span> <span class="va">$(</span><span class="fu">seq</span> 1 <span class="va">$DIRDEPTH)</span><span class="kw">;</span> <span class="cf">do</span></span>
<span id="cb3-9"><a href="#cb3-9" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>        <span class="va">RELPATH</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="va">$RELPATH</span><span class="st">&quot;/..&quot;</span></span>
<span id="cb3-10"><a href="#cb3-10" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a>    <span class="cf">done</span></span>
<span id="cb3-11"><a href="#cb3-11" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="cf">fi</span></span>
<span id="cb3-12"><a href="#cb3-12" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="fu">sed</span> <span class="at">--in-place</span> <span class="st">&quot;s,RELPATH,</span><span class="va">$RELPATH</span><span class="st">,g&quot;</span> <span class="st">&quot;</span><span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span><span class="st">&quot;</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>or insert last modification date from <code>git</code>:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb4"><pre class="sourceCode bash"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb4-1"><a href="#cb4-1" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="co"># Add last modification date</span></span>
<span id="cb4-2"><a href="#cb4-2" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="va">LASTMODIFIED</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="kw">`</span><span class="fu">git</span> log <span class="at">-1</span> <span class="at">--pretty</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;format:%cs&quot;</span> <span class="va">$SRCDIR</span>/<span class="va">$FILEPATH</span><span class="kw">`</span></span>
<span id="cb4-3"><a href="#cb4-3" aria-hidden="true" tabindex="-1"></a><span class="fu">sed</span> <span class="at">--in-place</span> <span class="st">&quot;s,LASTMODIFIED,</span><span class="va">$LASTMODIFIED</span><span class="st">,g&quot;</span> <span class="st">&quot;</span><span class="va">$HTMLFILE</span><span class="st">&quot;</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>I like to keep all my projects organized, and so files that comprise the website
are placed into dedicated directories. For example, all images are placed in
<code>img</code> directory, while all kinds of resources (e.g. web fonts, a unique
non-generated 404 page, favicon) are in the <code>res</code> folder:</p>
<pre><code>fremenzone
├── css
├── docs
├── img
├── res
├── src
└── templates</code></pre>
<p>In order for all these files to form a coherent page that can be displayed in a
browser, they must be assembled into one directory - <code>docs</code>. This was initially
done by the same bash script that generated the pages from templates. The
script would first copy all images, resources and CSS files to <code>docs</code>, and then
it would proceed to generate <em>all</em> HTML pages, regardless of whether they were
changed or not.</p>
<p>This approach was very easy to program and worked well at first. However, as I
added more subpages, the approach of rebuilding every HTML page became a bit too
slow. Obviously, it wasn’t very slow, but slow enough that I had to
deliberately pause before pressing F5 in the browser after making changes to the
sources. It was time to write a proper <code>Makefile</code> for the page.</p>
<p>With a <code>Makefile</code> in place, only the modified files are regenerated. No more
rebuilding of all the HTML sources or copying of the whole image directory.
Switching the build process to <code>make</code> made rebuilding the modified sources two
orders of magnitude faster. The caveat is that rebuilding the whole website,
for example after calling <code>make clean</code>, is actually several times slower than
with the bash script. However, that is a corner case that happens very rarely.
What matters is that the most common use case has been optimized.</p>
<h2 id="polishing-the-details">Polishing the details</h2>
<p>At various moments during Fremen Zone development, I’ve spent quite significant
amounts of time on getting the various details right.</p>
<h3 id="html-validation">HTML validation</h3>
<p>First and foremost, I wanted to ensure that I write correct HTML. To this end,
I wrote a bash script that checks all the generated pages using
<a href="https://www.html-tidy.org/">html-tidy</a>, and created a dedicated <code>make</code> target
to be able to call it easily. The next step was to set up a GitHub action that
calls the script on every commit, just in case I miss something during local
development. Additionally, just to be extra sure, I’ve set up a <a href="https://github.com/Cyb3r-Jak3/html5validator-action">GitHub
action</a> that checks
generated pages using
<a href="https://github.com/svenkreiss/html5validator">html5validator</a>.</p>
<h3 id="rss-feed">RSS feed</h3>
<p>One of the things I absolutely wanted to have on my page was an RSS feed.
Again, I didn’t want to rely on any generators - this might not have even been
possible, given that Fremen Zone does not take a format of a blog - which forced
me to dive into <a href="https://cyber.harvard.edu/rss/rss.html">RSS specification</a>.
Luckily, it’s not that complex, but it took some effort to make things work as
intended. Not everything was clear from the specification, forcing me to peek
into various generated feeds, such as the one generated by Hakyll for this blog.
I also mixed in elements of
<a href="https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/atom.html">Atom</a>, so the feed isn’t purely
in the RSS format.</p>
<h3 id="web-fonts">Web fonts</h3>
<p>Once an RSS feed was ready, I wanted to have an RSS icon in the navigation bar.
This was surprisingly tricky to get right. After quite a substantial amount of
research and experimentation, I figured out that the only reliable method that
works on multiple different browsers is to use a dedicated glyph from an
embedded web font. I went with an older version (5.15.4) of
<a href="https://github.com/FortAwesome/Font-Awesome/">FontAwesome</a> web fonts in two
different formats, <a href="https://caniuse.com/woff">woff</a> and
<a href="https://caniuse.com/woff2">woff2</a>, the former one for those poor souls that use
unbelievably outdated web browsers. Using a web font also solved the problem of
displaying an icon for “hamburger menu” on mobile devices.</p>
<h3 id="optimizing-loading-times">Optimizing loading times</h3>
<p>At some point, I spent quite a significant amount of time on figuring out how to
optimize Fremen Zone for faster loading. I admit that I am a beginner when it
comes to the topic and I had to rely on pieces of advice found online - often
conflicting, forcing me to dive deeper into HTML5 specification and browser
documentation. One simple thing was to use a CSS minifier, a program that
strips whitespaces and comments from a CSS file, making it more than 50%
smaller. I also experimented with HTML minifiers, but couldn’t find one that
would actually work without breaking the page and violating the HTML5 standard.</p>
<p>The next step in optimizing the loading times was related to embedded web fonts.
Firstly, it is possible to strip the redundant glyphs from a font file. I only
needed two glyphs from each of the two font files (woff, woff2), which allowed
me to reduce file sizes from 40-50kB, to less than a kilobyte. Secondly, it is
possible to preload the web fonts, i.e. instruct the browser in the HTML header
to start loading the font files before the rest of the page is parsed and the
glyphs from the font are actually requested. It is also possible to preload the
CSS and other resources, which I did. I’m not exactly sure whether this has any
benefits - the measurements I made using the browser’s developer tools were
inconclusive. However, there seems to be no costs of attempting a preload, so I
decided to keep it. For a brief moment I also experimented with <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/Performance/Lazy_loading">lazy image
loading</a>,
but realized that’s one of the features I absolutely hate on the web and dropped
the whole idea.</p>
<h3 id="improving-accessibility-with-alt-attributes">Improving accessibility with <code>alt</code> attributes</h3>
<p>When I set up the HTML validators, I got a bunch of warnings about missing <code>alt</code>
attributes for the <code>&lt;img&gt;</code> tags. This turned out to be another rabbit hole, as
I spent several hours trying to understand what <code>alt</code> attribute should contain.
And then I spent even more time writing the contents of those attributes. Long
story short, <code>alt</code> attribute should describe the contents of an image. Just
imagine someone asking you “what’s in this picture?” and you go to describe what
the image depicts. In the future, I’d like to learn more about making a web page
accessible for people using screen readers. Providing meaningful <code>alt</code> tags is
a small first step towards that goal.</p>
<h2 id="hosting-the-site">Hosting the site</h2>
<p>I don’t expect Fremen Zone to generate large traffic, and so for the time being
I decided GitHub Pages should suffice as a hosting provider. There was a small
catch, though. GitHub Pages can only host websites available in a public
repository, at least on the free plan. However, I didn’t want to expose any of
the in-progress work, notes, etc. The solution was handed to my by a colleague
from work and is in fact trivial: use two repositories, a private one for
development and a public one for hosting. For this reason, if you go to <a href="https://github.com/jstolarek/fremenzone">Fremen
Zone repository</a> you will only find the
generated HTML files, LICENSE and README files as well as definitions of GitHub
workflows. All the scripts discussed in this post are in the private repo.</p>
<p>To make updating of the public repository easier I created another dedicated
script that performs a bunch of safety checks (no untracked files, no
uncommitted changes, no unaddressed TODOs, etc.), and, if those pass, builds the
page from sources and copies the resulting files to the public repository. I
then need to manually commit and push the changes, which is another safety
measure against publishing something unintended.</p>
<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>Front-end development is definitely not my cup of tee, but creating a website
from scratch using only HTML and CSS was actually quite a lot of fun. By
relying on the most basic technologies, I expect the site to be future-proof and
easy to move to different hosting, once such a need arises.</p>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>21/08/2024</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2024-08-21-fremen-zone-creating-a-website-using-only-html-and-css.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Invincible. A game review</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 31/05/2024
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="the-invincible.-a-game-review">The Invincible. A game review</h1>
<p>One of the games I awaited impatiently in 2023 was <a href="https://www.gog.com/game/the_invincible">The
Invincible</a>, a debut game by Polish
developer Starward Industries and an adaptation of a hard sci-fi novel by
Stanisław Lem, written in 1964. Stanisław Lem is one of my favourite authors,
and <em>The Invincible</em> stands amongst his best works. I had an opportunity to
play a demo version of the game back in May 2023 during <a href="https://pixelheavenfest.com">Pixel
Heaven</a> and, despite some minor hiccups that could
be excused in a development build, the game looked very promising. The game
finally released in early November, and I just had to play it ASAP. Sadly, this
blog post itself is long overdue. While I wrote a huge part of it right after
finishing the game back in November, well over six months ago, I only managed to
wrap it up now.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/title.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/title_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Title screen.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<h2 id="need-a-hint">Need a hint?</h2>
<p>The game takes place on planet Regis III. You play as Dr Yasna, a crew member
of the Dragonfly, that wakes up with amnesia. You are alone and disoriented.
After reading a bunch of notes-to-self, you set out towards your expedition’s
camp, which you conjecture has to be nearby.</p>
<p>Amnesiac protagonist is one of the most abused tropes in games and is typically
an attempt to make up for poor writing. That was a big red flag right at the
start of the game. By the time I reached the said camp, I had a whole forest of
red flags.</p>
<p>The Invincible is a walking simulator, Firewatch style. You walk, and you
interact with objects: flip through the notes, open the doors, turn the dials,
etc. With no HUD and all cutscenes being first-person, the game tries to be as
immersive as possible. This is a great idea, but the execution is lacking. The
player surroundings are cluttered with interaction hints, making you wonder what
was the point of not having a HUD.</p>
<p>In particular, the game environment cannot be traversed freely. Dr Yasna can’t
jump, and terrain obstacles can only be climbed in places chosen by the
designers. However, traversable terrain is not distinguished visually in any
way, and so all ledges that can be climbed need to be highlighted with
interaction hints, significantly impacting the immersion achieved via
first-person narration.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/ledge.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/ledge_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Traversable ledges are marked with interaction hints. This one here is obvious. Most are not.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In theory, interaction hints can be disabled in the game’s settings. In
practice, this results in having to randomly click on all surrounding objects,
trying to figure out where is the object that the game expects you to interact
with. I made a brief experiment of playing with hints at the beginning of the
game, but without them the game is barely playable.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/map_hints.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/map_hints_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Turn these hints off, and you’ll be forced to click randomly on the map.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>On top of the interaction hints, there are also mission hints that tell you what
to do next. And what do these hints tell you? “Continue marching towards the
camp”. “Keep following the road to Condor”. “Finish the conversation”. I’m
sorry to say this, but if a walking simulator, or any game for that matter,
needs to tell you to keep doing what you’re already doing, then something is
off. In truth, these hints are completely redundant, since the game really does
a good job of communicating what needs to be done. These mission hints take
away what little is left of player agency, and sadly they can’t be turned off.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/just_go.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/just_go_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Do I really need to be reminded to continue walking on a straight road?
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/gorsky.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/gorsky_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Many of the hints are useless.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>One final gameplay complaint is that the game severely limits your ability to
run. You can sprint for a couple of seconds, and then Yasna is out of breath
and needs to walk. Well, I suppose the creators really wanted this to be a
walking simulator, not a running simulator.</p>
<h2 id="blessed-those-who-not-having-anything-to-say-do-not-try-to-put-it-into-words">Blessed those, who not having anything to say, do not try to put it into words</h2>
<p>The plot of The Invincible is delivered in monologues of the main protagonist,
and once she regains communication with the Dragonfly in dialogues with an
astrogator. I found most of the monologues extremely tiring. Dr Yasna babbles
endlessly, commenting on dozens of unimportant things. And when she runs out of
things to comment, she begins to hum and sing. She just doesn’t shut up. This
turned the first 30 minutes of the game into an ordeal. Luckily, the dialogues
were more meaningful, and thus interesting. However, longer dialogues (of which
there are quite a few) often disable the ability to interact with the
environment, forcing the player to listen through the dialogue before allowing
interactions with objects, and thus progress. In a similar spirit, in certain
scenes the player will be either immobilized or otherwise blocked from leaving
the place. This is exactly what I meant earlier when I said the player has
little agency. Conversely, in a couple of places where I was actually allowed
to walk during a dialogue, I reached a place that triggered a new dialogue,
ending prematurely the previous one.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/yasna.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/yasna_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Can you please be quiet for just one second?
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<h2 id="the-plot">The plot?</h2>
<p>But perhaps I shouldn’t be so harsh on the gameplay? After all, this is a
walking simulator and these are not played for their elaborate game mechanics.
Rather, the quality of a walking simulator lies in how well it tells a story.
This is where <em>The Invincible</em> does a somewhat better job.</p>
<p>As already mentioned in the introduction, <em>The Invincible</em> is based on a novel
by Stanisław Lem. The plot revolves around solving the mysteries encountered on
Regis III. Firstly, why do you have an amnesia? (And luckily there is a good
reason for it, so it’s not just a tool to make up for bad storytelling.) As you
make it to the camp, you discover, that some of your colleagues have gone lost,
while others are in a stupor. Hence, the second question: what happened to your
colleagues? You will also quickly discover, that there are other humans on the
planet. Unfortunately for you, they are from a hostile fraction. Luckily (?),
their expedition has been decimated, just as yours. And so the last mystery:
what else is on this planet?</p>
<p>If you read the book, then you will immediately know the answer to the last
question. Thus, the unravelling of the mystery of Regis III won’t be as
impactful as it will be for players unfamiliar with Lem’s novel. However, <em>The
Invincible</em> takes some liberties in adapting the original work, and thus there
are surprises waiting for the fans of Lem. I am not going to spoil them here.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, plot delivery isn’t perfect. I already mentioned some problems
in the previous section: meaningless monologues, listening to dialogues that
play out with no player agency or explicitly telling the player what to do in
form of intrusive hints. In addition to that, there are several deus
ex machina moments, where the protagonist is miraculously saved from what should
have been a certain death.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/bot.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/bot_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
The protagonist is exceptionally good at escaping certain death.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<h2 id="a-long-hike-on-regis-iii">A long hike on Regis III</h2>
<p>There is one thing that <em>The Invincible</em> does flawlessly: the world vision. The
surface of Regis III is meticulously designed and visually stunning. I mean,
just look:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/regis_1.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/regis_1_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/regis_2.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/regis_2_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/regis_3.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/regis_3_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/regis_4.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/regis_4_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/regis_5.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/regis_5_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/regis_6.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/regis_6_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/regis_7.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/regis_7_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In addition to that, all machines and vehicles are designed in a
retro-futuristic style, evoking the look of science-fiction movies from half a
century ago. This gives the game a unique, fresh feel. Overall, the graphics
and art direction are the game’s biggest strengths.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/retro_1.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/retro_1_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/retro_2.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/retro_2_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/retro_3.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/retro_3_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/retro_4.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/retro_4_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/retro_5.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/retro_5_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/retro_6.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review/retro_6_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The soundtrack also deserves praise. Though it’s not the kind of music that you
are going to remember after finishing the game, it does a good job of building
the mood.</p>
<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>I bought <em>The Invincible</em> on the day of its release, something that I don’t do
very often. I don’t regret paying the full price, and I don’t regret the time
spent with the game (around 7 hours or so), but the game wasn’t as good as I
hoped for. Restrictive gameplay (excessive hints, no player agency) and
annoying protagonist make for a frustrating gaming experience. If I were to
rate <em>The Invincible</em>, I’d say it’s a 6.5 out of 10 game. I would recommend
giving it a try, but perhaps wait to grab it on sale. What I can recommend
without the slightest hesitation though is reading the Lem’s original novel. If
you like hard sci-fi, you will enjoy it.</p>
<p>Also, having waited so long to publish this post, I now know that the game did
not sell as well as the Starward Industries had hoped for. Sadly, this resulted
in <a href="https://www.cdaction.pl/newsy/polskie-starward-industries-pozegnalo-sie-z-15-pracownikami">laying off 15 out of 34
employees</a>.
The developer isn’t giving up, however, and <a href="https://www.cdaction.pl/newsy/the-invincible-tworcy-gradaptacji-lema-nie-poddaja-sie-bedzie-masa-zawartosci">plans several big updates for the
game</a>,
hoping for the long tail. I am curious what the end result is going to be,
though I doubt this will fix the game biggest flaws. And let’s face it, having
completed this game once, there is really no reason to play it for the second
time.</p>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>31/05/2024</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2024-05-31-the-invincible-a-game-review.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>My favourite bands are coming back to life and I love it</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2024-05-29-my-favourite-bands-are-coming-back-to-life-and-i-love-it.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 29/05/2024
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="my-favourite-bands-are-coming-back-to-life-and-i-love-it">My favourite bands are coming back to life and I love it</h1>
<p>My late teens and early 20s have been a formative period for my musical taste.
It was back then when I started listening to hardcore/punk rock and its
derivatives such as metalcore and, most importantly of all, post-hardcore. The
latter is a broad genre and many bands have received a post-hardcore label, but
my top favourites are Alexisonfire<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a> and From Autumn to Ashes.</p>
<p>From my perspective, years between 2003 and 2005 feel like a golden period of
music. If I were to make a list of great albums released in those years, I
could easily pick at least fifty. Sadly, as time went on, most of the bands I
liked either officially disbanded or silently went on an indefinite hiatus.
Reasons were many: starting a family and living a life, working on another
musical project, or sometimes an argument within a band that made former friends
part their ways. This always made me sad, but I learned to move on and just
enjoy the old recordings.</p>
<p>But in recent years I am seeing a reverse trend: many bands that were at their
peak 20 years ago are now re-forming and recording new music. I am not sure why
that is happening, though the collective loneliness and uncertainty of the
pandemic seems to have been a contributing factor in at least some of the cases.
In this post, I want to highlight three new records from the last two years that
have been extremely pleasant surprises for me. Perhaps you will enjoy them too.</p>
<h2 id="intermission-bandcamp-is-doing-music-distribution-the-right-way">Intermission: Bandcamp is doing music distribution the right way</h2>
<p>I like buying physical album releases, but since I don’t have enough space to
store all the music that I listen to, I also like the idea of digital
distribution. However, execution of that idea is often poor, either because of
DRM or because music is being provided as a service. In both cases, one does
not receive ownership of what one pays for. To me, that is unacceptable.</p>
<p>Enter <a href="https://bandcamp.com/">Bandcamp</a>.</p>
<p>Bandcamp is an online music distribution platform, that truly sells music -
both in digital form and on physical media. If you purchase an album or a track
you get to download it DRM-free in any of the most popular audio formats (MP3,
FLAC, OGG, WAV, AAC, ALAC, AIFF). Importantly, Bandcamp also allows you to
listen to albums for free before making a purchase. Hence, most links in this
post will lead you to Bandcamp.</p>
<p>In the past year, I’ve fallen in love with Bandcamp and now use it to make
almost all of my music purchases<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a>. Bandcamp isn’t yet as big and popular as
Spotify, so not all bands can be found there. Luckily for me, the ones I care
about are mostly there.</p>
<p>Anyway, let’s get to the music.</p>
<h2 id="otherness-by-alexisonfire"><em>Otherness</em> by Alexisonfire</h2>
<p>Alexisonfire is a post-hardcore band from Canada. They are one of my favourite
bands and I can’t help but truly appreciate their official website address,
<a href="https://theonlybandever.com/">theonlybandever.com</a>. The band released four
full-length albums between 2001 and 2008. They disbanded in 2010 and the
members went to play in various other bands (Gallows, City And Colour, Black
Lungs). If I were to pick Alexisonfire’s best album, I would have a hard time
deciding between <a href="https://alexisonfire.bandcamp.com/album/watch-out"><em>Watch
Out!</em></a> and
<a href="https://alexisonfire.bandcamp.com/album/crisis"><em>Crisis</em></a>.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-29-my-favourite-bands-are-coming-back-to-life-and-i-love-it/otherness.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-29-my-favourite-bands-are-coming-back-to-life-and-i-love-it/otherness_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
<em>Otherness</em> cover.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In June 2022 Alexisonfire released a new album called
<a href="https://alexisonfire.bandcamp.com/album/otherness"><em>Otherness</em></a>. It wasn’t
entirely unexpected since in 2019 the band released two new songs, <a href="https://alexisonfire.bandcamp.com/album/familiar-drugs">Familiar
Drugs</a> and
<a href="https://alexisonfire.bandcamp.com/album/complicit">Complicit</a>, followed by one
more song, <a href="https://alexisonfire.bandcamp.com/album/season-of-the-flood">Season Of The
Flood</a>, in early
2020.</p>
<p>One characteristic thing about Alexisonfire is that each of their albums
maintains the band’s characteristic style, but at the same time has its own
uniqueness that sets it apart. This is also true for <em>Otherness</em>, with the
album being noticeably calmer and slower than the earlier ones. While I prefer
faster music, <em>Otherness</em> is a real joy to listen to. I also appreciate the
band experimenting with new sounds, such as in the song <a href="https://alexisonfire.bandcamp.com/track/dark-night-of-the-soul">Dark Night Of The
Soul</a>. If I
were to recommend one song from <em>Otherness</em> it would be <a href="https://alexisonfire.bandcamp.com/track/reverse-the-curse">Reverse The
Curse</a>.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-29-my-favourite-bands-are-coming-back-to-life-and-i-love-it/otherness_cd.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-29-my-favourite-bands-are-coming-back-to-life-and-i-love-it/otherness_cd_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
The physical version of the album comes with a lyrics booklet.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I also highly recommend <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4WOyIMbk_as">Alexisonfire’s House of Strombo
concert</a> on YouTube. It is under
40 minutes and contains music from all periods of their career.</p>
<h2 id="endless-by-leiah"><em>Endless</em> by Leiah</h2>
<p>Leiah is an emo band from Sweden, that released four records (EP + three albums)
between 1999 and 2003 and then went completely silent. Note that when I say
“emo” I don’t mean the kind of emo that became popular mainstream in the
mid-late 2000s. Rather, Leiah follows in the footsteps of bands such <a href="https://sunnydayrealestate.bandcamp.com">Sunny Day
Real Estate</a> or Mineral. While Leiah
was never at the top of my favourite bands, they are certainly a band that I
like and enjoy listening to. Especially in winter.</p>
<p>Leiah was always a band I found quite cryptic. For long, long years there was
no information about them available online: no Wikipedia page, no social media,
nothing available on the streaming services, no online search results. It was
as if the band never existed. Things changed in January 2018, when the band
opened an <a href="https://www.instagram.com/leiah026/">Instagram account</a>, released
<a href="https://leiah.bandcamp.com/">remastered versions</a> of their first three albums,
and went on a tour in 2019. I wasn’t aware of this return to activities and
only learned about it when Leiah released their new album, called
<a href="https://thirtysomethingrecords.bandcamp.com/album/endless"><em>Endless</em></a>, in
January 2023. As such, it took me completely by surprise - a very pleasant
surprise, I must add.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-29-my-favourite-bands-are-coming-back-to-life-and-i-love-it/endless.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-29-my-favourite-bands-are-coming-back-to-life-and-i-love-it/endless_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
<em>Endless</em> cover.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><em>Endless</em> is 39 minutes long and features ten songs. The music is similar in
style to Leiah’s earlier releases, but at the same time it feels genuinely fresh
and new. It is a comeback that is so good it almost feels unreal. If I were to
recommend one song from the new album, it would be
<a href="https://thirtysomethingrecords.bandcamp.com/track/surrender">Surrender</a>.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-29-my-favourite-bands-are-coming-back-to-life-and-i-love-it/endless_cd.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-29-my-favourite-bands-are-coming-back-to-life-and-i-love-it/endless_cd_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
The physical release comes with four bonus tracks (14 total). Sadly, no lyrics booklet.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>When it comes to Leiah’s older songs, I highly recommend
<a href="https://leiah.bandcamp.com/track/week-end">Week-End</a> from the album
<a href="https://leiah.bandcamp.com/album/surrounded-by-seasons"><em>Surrounded by
Seasons</em></a>.</p>
<h2 id="the-revealing-by-stretch-arm-strong"><em>The Revealing</em> by Stretch Arm Strong</h2>
<p>Stretch Arm Strong is an American melodic hardcore band, that released five
full-length albums between 1998 and 2005. The last one, <em>Free at Last</em>, is a
real masterpiece. Again, the band was almost completely silent for nearly two
decades. And then in March this year - 2024, in case you’re reading this in the
future - they released a new EP.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-05-29-my-favourite-bands-are-coming-back-to-life-and-i-love-it/the_revealing.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-05-29-my-favourite-bands-are-coming-back-to-life-and-i-love-it/the_revealing_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
<em>The Revealing</em> cover.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>With six songs, <em>The Revealing</em> is only 14 minutes long. This might not seem
like much, but the songs are really great. They are fast, aggressive, and full
of positive energy. While many bands drift towards softer music as they age,
this is certainly not the case here. <em>The Revealing</em> is pure energy, and I’ve
been listening to it several times a day for the past two weeks. If I were to
recommend just one song from the EP it would be <a href="https://stretcharmstrongsc.bandcamp.com/track/still-believe-part-iii">Still Believe, Part
III</a>.</p>
<p>My only complaint about <em>The Revealing</em> is that, as of the moment of this
writing, the CD version of the album is not available in Europe, leaving the
option of purchasing either a digital version or a vinyl.</p>
<p>I also note that while Stretch Arm Strong has re-issued two of their old albums
on vinyls, these albums cannot be purchased digitally on Bandcamp. Their
digital versions are only available as a bonus if you purchase the vinyl
release, which is a huge shame.</p>
<h2 id="still-waiting-for">Still waiting for…</h2>
<p>All the three releases above are great albums that brought me a lot of joy.
While over the years I experimented with new bands and genres, I still come back
to my favourite bands from two decades ago. Their music has a special place in
my heart and I am truly happy to see some of them come back to life.</p>
<p>I hope this is not the end of it. At this point, my biggest hopes are for a new
album from <a href="https://fromautumntoashes.bandcamp.com">From Autumn To Ashes</a>. In
the past few years, the band has been actively touring and releasing their
previous albums on vinyls. A new album feels like a next logical step. I keep
my finger crossed.</p>
<section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Pronounced as Alexis-on-fire, not Alex-is-on-fire.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>To be entirely fair, Bandcamp can sometimes feel like a bit of a mess.
The music is not organized by bands but rather by copyright owners. Sure,
you will see all albums of a band available on a single profile. But it
is also common to have albums of an artist sold across multiple different
profiles, often grouped with other artists signed to the same record
label. A good example is Shai Hulud, which has two different artist
profiles: one for <a href="https://shaihulud.bandcamp.com/music">albums released by Revelation
Records</a> and one for albums
<a href="https://shaihuludofficial.bandcamp.com/music">released by Metal Blade
Records</a>. The good news is
that once you purchase an album, it simply becomes available in your
collection and all that mess becomes irrelevant.<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>29/05/2024</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2024-05-29-my-favourite-bands-are-coming-back-to-life-and-i-love-it.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Installing an IPS-screen in a NeoGeo Pocket Color</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 20/01/2024
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="installing-an-ips-screen-in-a-neogeo-pocket-color">Installing an IPS-screen in a NeoGeo Pocket Color</h1>
<p>About a year ago I bought two rather obscure handheld consoles: a NeoGeo Pocket
Color (NGPC) and a WonderSwan Color (WSC). Both were competitors to the GameBoy
Color (GBC) and both lost. Due to their smaller popularity they are not as well
known as the GameBoy and also command higher prices today, since there were
fever of them produces. Also, neither the NGPC nor the WSC had a backlit
screen, so in order to be used comfortably they need an IPS mod. Today I will
write about installing a modern IPS panel in the NGPC.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/original_screen_1.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/original_screen_1_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Original screen is usable only when under direct light.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Before moving on there’s an important disclaimer. NeoGeo Pocket comes in three
versions. There’s the original NeoGeo Pocket with a monochrome screen. It was
on the market for about a year (1998-1999) and never officially left Japan.
Then there is the NeoGeo Pocket Color that I will be talking about in this post.
It was distributed worldwide, even if only for a couple of months, but mine is a
Japanese unit. Finally, there’s a smaller version of NGPC, officially known as
the New NeoGeo Pocket Color. These days people commonly refer to it as NGPC
Slim. Due to smaller size NGPC Slim is more difficult to mod.</p>
<h2 id="about-the-mod">About the mod</h2>
<p>When modding the GameBoys I usually rely on parts from FunnyPlaying. However,
they only offer mods for the GameBoys. Looking at the online retro communities
it seems that when it comes to the NeoGeo Pocket people tend to order from the
<a href="https://pl.aliexpress.com/store/5374188">Cloud Game Store</a> on AliExpress. And
so I bought from them an IPS panel mod as well as a new replacement shell. The
choice of shells isn’t great to be honest. I went with a transparent black
shell and also ended up installing original black buttons from my console,
instead of clear transparent ones that came with the kit. Moreover, both the
IPS panel and the shell are noticeably more expensive than in case of the
GameBoys.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/kit_parts.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/kit_parts_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Kit parts.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<h2 id="installing-the-screen">Installing the screen</h2>
<p>For the most part installation is straightforward. First step is disassembly:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/ngpc_disassembly_1.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/ngpc_disassembly_1_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Original screen is solidly attached to the shell. Note the metal
backplate.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/ngpc_disassembly_2.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/ngpc_disassembly_2_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
These foam spacers need to be disassembled to make the new screen fit.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The first tricky bit is the metal cover separating the cartridge slot and the
main board. The one that comes with the kit doesn’t fit the shell very well so
I had to re-use the original one. However, reusing original screws was not a
good idea, as the screw holes are significantly smaller on the replacement
shell.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/slot_cover.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/slot_cover_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Metal slot cover I got with the shell didn’t fit very well.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/slot_cover_screws.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/slot_cover_screws_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Original screws are too big for the new shell and it just cracks.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Installing the screen itself turned out to be tricky. There is no spacing
bracket so one has to rely on a small plastic spacer and a piece of foam
provided with the kit. This is far from perfect. There is also a dust seal to
be used to permanently attach the IPS panel to the shell. However, the IPS
panel is quite narrow and so it only attaches to the top and bottom of the seal,
making it possible for the dust to come in from the sides. Also, at first I
couldn’t figure out the orientation of the panel, since it’s nearly square is
shape.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/screen_install_1.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/screen_install_1_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
A plastic spacer on the right, a foam spacer on the left.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/screen_install_2.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/screen_install_2_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
IPS panel and the controller board secured in place.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The board needs to be powered directly from the battery, which is done with an
extra wire. Installation instructions say to just wrap the wire around the
battery contact, but I decided to solder it contact point on the board instead.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/power_wire.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/power_wire_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Power wire soldered to a battery contact on the board. Note also a
touch sensor at the top.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>With the power wire in place the shell is ready for final assembly. At this
point the touch sensor needs to carefully aligned so that it touches the top of
the shell. It will allow adjusting the brightness as well as selecting one of
several available scanline modes. There are horizontal and vertical ones, as
well as a retro-pixel grid. Personally, I found scanlines to be way too dark so
I have them turned off. It is also possible to switch the screen to a
monochrome mode.</p>
<p>Here’s the finished build:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/kof.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/kof_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
King of Fighters R-2.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/ms2.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/ms2_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Metal Slug 2nd Mission.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A few quick thoughts on this kit:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Shell quality is good, but the fit could be somewhat better. The top of
the shell isn’t as tight as it should be, no matter how tightly I fix the
screws.</li>
</ol>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/shell_left.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/shell_left_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Left edge of the shell. The fit is tight here.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/shell_top.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc/shell_top_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Top edge of the shell. Front and back don’t come together as tight
as they should.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li><p>In order to get the speaker to fit I had to remove its metal protective
cover.</p></li>
<li><p>I messed up when attaching the lens and left a fingerprint underneath it.
What I learned is that once the lens is removed with a suction cup it can
be attached again, so I was able to get that fingerprint removed without
having to get a new lens.</p></li>
<li><p>I am yet to determine the battery life of the modded system. I had the
console power off without a warning a couple of times. The original system
supposedly runs for as long as 40 hours on a pair of AA batteries, but an
IPS panel and a flashcart certainly reduce that time. I hope this
unexpected powering off isn’t a sign of a deeper problem.</p></li>
</ol>
<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>Over the course of time I was able to get a couple of original games for the
system (sadly, cartridges only - no boxes) but I also got a <a href="https://www.retrotowers.co.uk/flash-carts/neopocket-gamedrive">NeoPocket
GameDrive</a>
flashcart. Without a flashcart it’s really difficult to enjoy the system since
the game prices for NGPC are very high. Compared to the Everdrive cartridges
from Krikzz, the GameDrive is moderately convenient to use. It has 15MB of
flash memory and the games need to be loaded from an SD card into that memory
before they can be played. Once a game is loaded it stays in flash until you
delete it. 15 MB is enough to store several games, but the flashing process is
very slow, so if you want to play multiple titles you might find yourself
waiting quite a lot.</p>
<p>As for the games themselves I was afraid that NGPC will be nothing more than an
expensive curiosity, but it actually has quite a lot to offer. At least for a
NeoGeo MVS fan like myself. I spent a lot of time playing arcade titles such as
Metal Slug, King of Fighters, Samurai Shodown, and The Last Blade. All of these
titles have their NGPC ports, though calling them “ports” is a bit of a stretch.
Today we would call them demakes. Regardless of how we call them however, they
are a blast to play. I was genuinely surprised that despite simple graphics -
the character sprites consist of only three colours - The Last Blade plays just
like in the arcade version. Same goes for King of Fighters and SNK vs. Capcom.
These games are so enjoyable not only because of how responsive they are and how
accurately they recreate the arcade feel of original titles, but also thanks to
the joystick that the NGPC uses. Instead of the usual D-pad the console has a
small, clicky joystick, and that joystick makes it possible to easily execute
all the tricky inputs required in fighting games. This is in stark contrast
with, say, GameBoy Advance, which offers arcade-perfect ports of King of Fighters
games, but the D-pad makes it nearly impossible to reliably execute any special
moves.</p>
<p>Also I’d love to be able to play some fighting games in the Versus mode between
two consoles. This doesn’t seem likely though, given that link cables to
connect two consoles are practically unavailable on the second-hand market. And
when they are they sell for well over a hundred dollars.</p>
<p>That being said, I will certainly be looking to get one more NeoGeo Pocket, this
time possibly a Slim variant. This console has certainly turned out to be much
more than I expected.</p>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>20/01/2024</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2024-01-21-installing-ips-screen-in-ngpc.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Installing X-Reset and DFO mods in my PlayStation</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-12-18-installing-x-reset-and-dfo-in-my-psx.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 18/12/2023
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="installing-x-reset-and-dfo-mods-in-my-playstation">Installing X-Reset and DFO mods in my PlayStation</h1>
<center>
<strong>DISCLAIMER:</strong> This post is not intended to serve as installation tutorial.
</center>
<p>I recently wrote about <a href="2023-11-30-installing-a-gcloader-in-my-gamecube.html">installing a GCLoader in a GameCube I
own</a>, but on the same day
I also installed two additional mods in my PlayStation: an <a href="https://www.consolesunleashed.com/product/sony-playstation-x-reset-mod-kit/">X-Reset
mod</a>
and a <a href="https://www.consolesunleashed.com/product/sony-playstation-dual-frequency-oscillator-mod-kit/">DFO
mod</a>,
both purchased from <a href="https://www.consolesunleashed.com/">Consoles Unleashed</a>.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-12-18-installing-x-reset-and-dfo-in-my-psx/x-reset-and-dfo.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-12-18-installing-x-reset-and-dfo-in-my-psx/x-reset-and-dfo_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
X-Reset on the left and DFO on the right.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<h2 id="x-reset">X-Reset</h2>
<p>I already <a href="2023-03-35-installing-xstation.html">installed XStation in my PSX</a>,
which is an optical drive emulator (ODE) that allows launching games from ISO
images stored on an SD card. While it’s super convenient to have all games on a
single memory card, there was a minor usability issue related to using XStation.
Resetting the console to return to XStation’s game selection menu required
physically pushing button on the console. Not a big deal, but somewhat annoying
when you’re sitting on a couch and want to quickly test a bunch of games.
X-Reset fixes that by adding button combinations to the controller that allow to
reset both the game (back to the title screen) and the console (back to
XStation’s game selection menu). Installation of X-Reset requires soldering a
small QSB (quick solder board) to the bottom of the motherboard.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-12-18-installing-x-reset-and-dfo-in-my-psx/x-reset-preperation.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-12-18-installing-x-reset-and-dfo-in-my-psx/x-reset-preperation_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Fixing the QSB in place with Kapton tape before soldering.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-12-18-installing-x-reset-and-dfo-in-my-psx/x-reset-installed.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-12-18-installing-x-reset-and-dfo-in-my-psx/x-reset-installed_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
X-Reset soldered to the motherboard. Note a poor solder joint in
the middle.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<h2 id="dfo">DFO</h2>
<p>I have a PAL-region console, where the games were timed to run at 50Hz.
Obviously, playing at 60Hz results in smoother experience and a PAL PlayStation
with XStation installed can actually switch to displaying 60Hz signal when
running NTSC games<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a>. However, when a PAL console runs an NTSC game the GPU
timings are slightly incorrect, resulting in a refresh rate that’s off by around
1 percent. This is rather unnoticeable, but certain games will not work because
of that difference.</p>
<p>This can be fixed with a DFO mod. DFO stands for Dual Frequency Oscillator. As
the name suggests, it allows to automatically<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a> supply different GPU timings
depending on the game region, thus ensuring that games run at correct speed both
in 50Hz and 60Hz.</p>
<p>Installing the mod is a bit tricky. As you can see from the photos below the
mod requires soldering four wires to the motherboard. That’s the simple part.
The difficult part is desoldering a resistor in order to disconnect the GPU from
the original frequency oscillator. That resistor is located under the RF shield
that covers top of the motherboard. The RF shield needs to be desoldered and
this was a difficult task. I was unable to fully desolder it and resorted to
lifting it as much as possible to remove the resistor. It worked, but I can’t
say I felt confident doing that.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-12-18-installing-x-reset-and-dfo-in-my-psx/rf-shield.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-12-18-installing-x-reset-and-dfo-in-my-psx/rf-shield_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
That metal plate is the RF shield. It is fixed to the board with
large blobs of solder that are difficult to remove.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-12-18-installing-x-reset-and-dfo-in-my-psx/removed-resistor.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-12-18-installing-x-reset-and-dfo-in-my-psx/removed-resistor_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
I managed to lift the RF shield just enough to remove the resistor.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-12-18-installing-x-reset-and-dfo-in-my-psx/dfo-installed.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-12-18-installing-x-reset-and-dfo-in-my-psx/dfo-installed_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Soldering the DFO board is the easy part.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>Both mods required fairly simple soldering. I’ve certainly done more
complicated mods, but this time something went wrong and I really messed up the
solder joints. They hold, but they don’t turned out the way they should.
Either my soldering iron is giving out or I messed up when using rosin, which I
hadn’t used previously.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-12-18-installing-x-reset-and-dfo-in-my-psx/bad-soldering.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-12-18-installing-x-reset-and-dfo-in-my-psx/bad-soldering_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Poor quality solder joints. I fixed them after taking these photos
but they are still not as good as they should be.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-12-18-installing-x-reset-and-dfo-in-my-psx/all-mods.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-12-18-installing-x-reset-and-dfo-in-my-psx/all-mods_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Bottom of my PlayStation’s motherboard. The large QSB on the left
is from previously installed XStation.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>I am committing a crime here by equating PAL with 50Hz refresh rate and
NTSC with 60Hz refresh rate. There is a common misconception that PAL and
NTSC standards prescribe a particular refresh rate, but that is not the
case. Both PAL and NTSC are colour coding standards and nothing else.
They do not define refresh rates.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>I am very curious how that actually works. How does a simple mod
connected with only four cables recognize the game region?<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>18/12/2023</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-12-18-installing-x-reset-and-dfo-in-my-psx.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Installing a GCLoader in my GameCube</title>
    <link>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-11-30-installing-a-gcloader-in-my-gamecube.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on 30/11/2023
    </section>
    <section>
        <h1 id="installing-a-gcloader-in-my-gamecube">Installing a GCLoader in my GameCube</h1>
<p>I got a GameCube towards the end of my stay in the UK, in late 2021. Right from
the start I wanted to mod it with a
<a href="https://gc-loader.com/product/gc-loader-pnp-hw2/">GCLoader</a>, which is an ODE
(Optical Drive Emulator) that replaces the original DVD drive, but it was
permanently out of stock. This was due to chip shortage caused by the pandemic,
followed by the FPGA chip used in the GCLoader going completely out of
production. As a stop-gap solution I had to install a <a href="https://www.consolesunleashed.com/product/nintendo-gamecube-region-free-mod-kit/">Xeno
modchip</a>
on the main board of the DVD drive:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-11-30-installing-a-gcloader-in-my-gamecube/modchip.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-11-30-installing-a-gcloader-in-my-gamecube/modchip_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Xeno modchip secured with Kapton tape.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A quick note on the photo above. As you can see the modchip is soldered
directly onto the DVD drive board, exactly as it was designed to be installed.
This required some fine soldering, with some solder points being less than 0,3mm
away from each other. I was advised to install the modchip not by soldering it
onto the board, but by soldering wires onto the contact points on the board and
then connecting these wires to the modchip. I ignored this advice, which I now
regret a bit. Having the modchip on wires would make it trivial to remove it,
and thus allow to easily restore the drive to its original state. De-soldering
the modchip from the board itself is a lot more complicated and I am not going
to risk it.</p>
<p>Installing the modchip allowed me to launch <a href="https://github.com/emukidid/swiss-gc">Swiss
homebrew</a> from a burned DVD, which then
automatically booted into the latest version of Swiss installed on a microSD
card inside an <a href="https://github.com/citrus3000psi/SD2SP2">SD2SP2 adapter</a>. From
a functionality perspective this setup provided everything I needed.</p>
<p>Recently the GCLoader was redesigned to use the currently available FPGA chip
and the ODE once again became available for purchase. Production batches are
small and they sell out very quickly. Luckily, they are announced in advance
and I managed to grab one unit in early November.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-11-30-installing-a-gcloader-in-my-gamecube/gcloader.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-11-30-installing-a-gcloader-in-my-gamecube/gcloader_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
The GCLoader, revision 2.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In the light of what I said above about the modchip and SD2SP2 setup it is right
to ask whether switching to a GCLoader makes any sense. After all, it doesn’t
provide any new functionality and it takes away the ability to run games from
original discs. Not to mention the cost of the ODE itself. These are all fair
points. However, GameCubes in recent years have seen frequent drive failures
due to decaying capacitors and I wanted to preempt such a failure on my console.
I should probably just recap the drive, but this is something I still don’t feel
confident with and want to avoid recapping if possible.</p>
<p>Installing the GCLoader is simple since it doesn’t require any soldering. All
it takes are a couple of screwdrivers, with the only caveat being the need for a
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_screw_drives#Line_Head_and_Line_Recess">Gamebit</a>
screwdriver.</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-11-30-installing-a-gcloader-in-my-gamecube/console-disassembled.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-11-30-installing-a-gcloader-in-my-gamecube/console-disassembled_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Disassembly is very straightforward. That’s the motherboard with a heatsink.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-11-30-installing-a-gcloader-in-my-gamecube/parts.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-11-30-installing-a-gcloader-in-my-gamecube/parts_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
And these are all the other parts, including a GameBoy Player and a network adapter.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-11-30-installing-a-gcloader-in-my-gamecube/installation-in-progress.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-11-30-installing-a-gcloader-in-my-gamecube/installation-in-progress_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
GCLoader attached to the drive mounting plate.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The only tricky bit is attaching the GCLoader to a metal plate on which the DVD
drive normally sits (last photo). The screws need to be a bit loose to allow
the GCLoader to move freely. This is because the holes in the plate are larger
than the GCLoader screws and so it is possible to move it around by about 1mm in
each direction. If it is fixed in a position that does not align with the port
on the main board there is a risk that resulting forces will eventually break
the solder points on either the GCLoader or the motherboard. By leaving the
screws slightly loose the GCLoader can easily move to the right position.</p>
<p>And here is the console right before final assembly:</p>
<div class="thumbnail">
<figure>
<a href="/images/posts/2023-11-30-installing-a-gcloader-in-my-gamecube/final-reassembly.jpg"><img src="/images/posts/2023-11-30-installing-a-gcloader-in-my-gamecube/final-reassembly_thumbnail.jpg" /></a>
<figcaption>
Final reassembly, just before installing top of the console case.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As you can see I installed a 3D printed SD mount on top of the GCLoader. Being
optimistic about the GCLoader availability, I got the SD mount shortly after I
bought the console. The SD mount waited for over two years in my drawer and I
am glad I can finally make use of it. I can’t remember where I bought the SD
mount, but I remember it was quite expensive. However, the plastic is of such a
high quality that I think this expense was fully justified.</p>
<p>After assembling the console I downloaded the latest Swiss and placed it on an
SD card as a <code>boot.iso</code> file. What really surprised me was that Swiss
recognized the outdated firmware of the GCLoader and informed me about the
available update. There is no way the console can download the update since it
has no Internet connectivity<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a>, but the fact that a sufficiently new version
of Swiss recognizes an outdated firmware is really neat.</p>
<p><strong>(UPDATE 10/12/2023):</strong> I ran into one small problem with the GCLoader, namely
slow loading times. In Swiss, when the game is loaded it is patched on the fly.
I’m not sure why, but that’s how it works. When I was launching the games using
SD2SP2 this patching and loading took around 5-6 seconds. With GCLoader it
takes around 25 seconds, which is noticeably longer. The solution to the
problem was to upgrade firmware from 1.0.1 to latest 1.1.0.BETA release. This
reduces the loading times to around 3 seconds, making the GCLoader slightly
faster than SD2SP2, as it should be.</p>
<section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>As you have seen in the above photos, I actually have a GameCube network
adapter. I bought it recently during a trip to London. However, it is
more of a curiosity though, since there were only a couple of games that
made use of online features.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>

        <p><a href="../blog.html">Back</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>30/11/2023</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jstolarek.github.io/posts/2023-11-30-installing-a-gcloader-in-my-gamecube.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Jan Stolarek</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
